<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Religion &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<atom:link href="https://dwaynedavies.com/category/religion/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://dwaynedavies.com</link>
	<description>Rational Nonfiction Author</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 14:19:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cropped-Ashna-Dwaynes-Wedding-23-crop-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Religion &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<link>https://dwaynedavies.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Islam &#8212; the Cause of 9/11</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ash Davies and Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 01:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[9/11]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[morality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[September 11]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[war]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=25767</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Islamic terrorism is the cause of 9/11, despite the evasion of many in America and the rest of the West. In this article we explore the proper response to such barbarism: crushing and demoralizing the enemy!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today we shall see that the cause of 9/11 is Islamic idealogy.</p>


<h2 class="simpletoc-title">Table of Contents</h2>
<ol class="simpletoc-list">
<li><a href="#htoc-february-26-1993-islam-attacks">February 26, 1993 &#8211; Islam Attacks</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="#htoc-most-tyrants-gain-power-by-the-consent-of-the-people-and-thus-the-population-is-guilty-of-making-such-tyranny-possible">Most tyrants gain power by the consent of the people, and thus the population is guilty of making such tyranny possible.</a></li>
<li><a href="#htoc-the-nuclear-bombs-dropped-upon-japan-were-an-act-of-heroism">The nuclear bombs dropped upon Japan were an act of heroism.</a></li>
<li><a href="#htoc-the-quran-contains-at-least-109-verses-describing-war-with-nonbelievers-many-are-quite-graphic-and-describe-things-such-as-the-decapitation-of-the-nonbeliever">The Quran contains at least 109 verses describing war with nonbelievers.</a></li>
<li><a href="#htoc-the-truth-is-that-islam-is-a-death-worshiping-cult-of-widespread-genocide">The truth is that Islam is a death-worshiping cult of widespread genocide.</a></li>
<li><a href="#htoc-but-we-have-seen-that-according-to-the-quran-itself-yousef-was-acting-entirely-consistent-with-the-quran">But we have seen that according to the Quran itself, Yousef was acting entirely consistent with the Quran.</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><a href="#htoc-september-11-2001-islam-attacks-again">September 11, 2001 &#8212; Islam Attacks Again</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-to-the-apologists-and-appeasers">To the Apologists and Appeasers</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="2/#htoc-islam-is-fundamentally-a-cult-of-violent-oppression-and-genocide-against-heretics-we-cannot-remove-this-from-the-religion-without-creating-a-fundamentally-different-religion">Islam is fundamentally a cult of violent oppression and genocide against heretics.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-those-rejecting-to-practice-this-tenet-of-the-religion-are-not-truly-devout-practitioners-of-islam">Those rejecting to practice this tenet of the religion are not truly devout practitioners of Islam.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-to-allow-islamic-states-to-threaten-the-west-is-an-act-of-cowardice">To allow Islamic States to threaten the West is an act of cowardice.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-if-we-hold-that-religion-is-anything-but-evil-then-we-cannot-identify-that-any-religion-is-the-enemy-we-must-fight">If we hold that religion is anything but evil, then we cannot identify that any religion is the enemy we must fight.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-if-we-wish-to-preserve-the-west-then-we-must-utterly-crush-demoralize-and-reveal-islam-for-the-weak-husk-that-it-would-be-when-divorced-from-the-support-of-the-good">If we wish to preserve the West, then we must utterly crush, demoralize and reveal Islam for the weak husk that it would be when divorced from the support of the good.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-we-are-not-saying-that-people-do-not-have-the-right-to-practice-religion">We are not saying that people do not have the right to practice religion.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-we-must-oppose-islamic-states-the-west-must-show-that-religion-has-no-ethical-or-political-power-in-its-lands">We must oppose Islamic States. The West must show that religion has no ethical or political power in its lands.</a></li>
</ol>
</li></ol>


<p>Before the Western values of reason and individuality were attacked by Islam, stood the twin towers of the World Trade Center. These mighty structures were icons of New York City, and they stood tall and proud. </p>



<p>Before 9/11, the twin towers stood as a symbol of the heights achievable by the efforts of reasoning individuals, who value productivity, self-esteem (ego), and rationality. They were a symbol of what is achievable by individuals in a culture that values freedoms and individual rights.</p>



<p>Much like the Statue of Liberty, they were symbols of Western values. A symbol of the American Dream rooted in every individual&#8217;s right to:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-life-liberty-and-the-pursuit-of-happiness">&#8220;Life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness&#8221;</p>
<cite>DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE</cite></blockquote>



<p>The American dream is that:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-life-should-be-better-and-richer-and-fuller-for-everyone-with-opportunity-for-each-according-to-ability-or-achievement"> Life should be better and richer and fuller for everyone, with opportunity for each according to ability or achievement. </p>
<cite>James Adams, 1931.</cite></blockquote>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-february-26-1993-islam-attacks">February 26, 1993 &#8211; Islam Attacks</h2>


<p>One of the first terrorist attack on these values came on February 26, 1993. An Islamic militant, Ramzi Yousef cowardly attacked Western values. Hus Islamic ideology killed six people and injured a further 1,042 people.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the 1998 trial, Yousef condemned the United States for its American Victory over Japan in 1945 and its economic embargo against a rights-violating Cuba. &nbsp;</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-you-keep-talking-also-about-collective-punishment-and-killing-innocent-people-to-force-governments-to-change-their-policies-you-call-this-terrorism-when-someone-would-kill-innocent-people-or-civilians-in-order-to-force-the-government-to-change-its-policies-well-when-you-were-the-first-one-who-invented-this-terrorism">You keep talking also about collective punishment and killing innocent people to force governments to change their policies; you call this terrorism when someone would kill innocent people or civilians in order to force the government to change its policies. Well, when you were the first one who invented this terrorism.</p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Here, Yousef clearly drops context and pretends the military defense of a nation is equivalent to terrorism if it involves the loss of innocent lives.</p>



<p>However, nobody that understands the moral justification of warfare would say such a thing. It is a moral imperative for a moral nation to engage in warfare with enemy nations and to inflict crushing military defeat upon them. </p>



<p>This always involves the loss of innocent lives. It is not feasible to expect to win a war against an enemy state without the loss of innocent lives in enemy nations. The blame for the loss of these innocent belongs to the enemy state. It is the enemy state that made the war necessary. The enemy state made it necessary to choose between innocent lives in the enemy state, or the loss of innocent lives in the nation defending itself.</p>



<p>However, the extent to which those innocent lives exist is not as great as most people think. </p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-most-tyrants-gain-power-by-the-consent-of-the-people-and-thus-the-population-is-guilty-of-making-such-tyranny-possible">Most tyrants gain power by the consent of the people, and thus the population is guilty of making such tyranny possible. </h3>


<p>It is immoral to equate warfare against an enemy state, a war of self-defense, with terrorism. To defend your nation against destruction by an enemy state can in no sense be equivalent to terrorism.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-you-were-the-first-one-who-killed-innocent-people-and-you-are-the-first-one-who-introduced-this-type-of-terrorism-to-the-history-of-mankind-when-you-dropped-an-atomic-bomb-which-killed-tens-of-thousands-of-women-and-children-in-japan-and-when-you-killed-over-a-hundred-thousand-people-most-of-them-civilians-in-tokyo-with-fire-bombings">You were the first one who killed innocent people, and you are the first one who introduced this type of terrorism to the history of mankind when you dropped an atomic bomb which killed tens of thousands of women and children in Japan and when you killed over a hundred thousand people, most of them civilians, in Tokyo with fire bombings. </p>



<p id="htoc-you-killed-them-by-burning-them-to-death-and-you-killed-civilians-in-vietnam-with-chemicals-as-with-the-so-called-agent-orange-you-killed-civilians-and-innocent-people-not-soldiers-innocent-people-every-single-war-you-went-you-went-to-wars-more-than-any-other-country-in-this-century-and-then-you-have-the-nerve-to-talk-about-killing-innocent-people">You killed them by burning them to death. And you killed civilians in Vietnam with chemicals, as with the so-called Agent Orange. You killed civilians and innocent people, not soldiers, innocent people every single war you went. You went to wars more than any other country in this century, and then you have the nerve to talk about killing innocent people.</p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia </cite></blockquote>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-nuclear-bombs-dropped-upon-japan-were-an-act-of-heroism">The nuclear bombs dropped upon Japan were an act of heroism. </h3>


<p>The alternative was a bloody invasion of the Japanese mainland that would have required the loss of over a million American lives, enormous expense, the destruction of much of Japan and the loss of millions of Japanese lives. </p>



<p>So it is that even the Japanese came to be thankful that the Americans found an alternative to an invasion of Japan that would have virtually destroyed Japan.</p>



<p>We must not judge the morality of a nation by the number of times it goes to war. There are legitimate reasons America may have needed to engage in war in self-defense. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced.jpg" alt="Ruins of Hiroshima." class="wp-image-26349" width="450" height="450" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced.jpg 600w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced-300x300.jpg 300w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Yes, doing this to Hiroshima was heroism. The alternative was doing this to most major Japanese cities.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>One can argue that many of the wars America has been involved in, such as the war in Vietnam or Iraq, were not justified in defending American interests but were altruistic campaigns. This is a legitimate reason to condemn America for many of its invasions.</p>



<p>But there is no legitimate reason to condemn America for Hiroshima and Nagasaki. They were a moral necessity as soon as Japan threatened America&#8217;s values of life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-and-now-you-have-invented-new-ways-to-kill-innocent-people-you-have-so-called-economic-embargo-which-kills-nobody-other-than-children-and-elderly-people-and-which-other-than-iraq-you-have-been-placing-the-economic-embargo-on-cuba-and-other-countries-for-over-35-years">And now you have invented new ways to kill innocent people. You have so-called economic embargo which kills nobody other than children and elderly people, and which other than Iraq you have been placing the economic embargo on Cuba and other countries for over 35 years. </p>



<p id="htoc-">&#8230; </p>



<p id="htoc-the-government-in-its-summations-and-opening-statement-said-that-i-was-a-terrorist-yes-i-am-a-terrorist-and-i-am-proud-of-it-and-i-support-terrorism-so-long-as-it-was-against-the-united-states-government-and-against-israel-because-you-are-more-than-terrorists-you-are-the-one-who-invented-terrorism-and-using-it-every-day-you-are-liars-butchers-and-hypocrites-29">The Government in its summations and opening statement said that I was a terrorist. Yes, I am a terrorist, and I am proud of it. And I support terrorism so long as it was against the United States Government and against Israel because you are more than terrorists; you are the one who invented terrorism and using it every day. You are liars, butchers, and hypocrites. <sup><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramzi_Yousef#cite_note-FullExcerpt-29">[29]</a></sup></p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia</cite></blockquote>



<p>Yousef condemns America for acts of violence and terrorism. He condemns America for acts of war and violence and for inventing terrorism.</p>



<p>Yet, Islam was engaging in religious terrorism long before the United States existed. It certainly did not invent terrorism, but it advocated terrorism long before America existed and long before modern Western culture existed.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-quran-contains-at-least-109-verses-describing-war-with-nonbelievers-many-are-quite-graphic-and-describe-things-such-as-the-decapitation-of-the-nonbeliever">The Quran contains at least 109 verses describing war with nonbelievers.</h3>


<p>Many of the verses are quite graphic and describe things such as the decapitation of the nonbeliever. </p>



<p>Here are some of them:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-as-to-those-who-reject-faith-i-will-punish-them-with-terrible-agony-in-this-world-and-in-the-hereafter-nor-will-they-have-anyone-to-help"><em>As to those who reject faith, I will punish them with terrible agony in this world and in the Hereafter, nor will they have anyone to help.</em></p>
<cite>Quran 3:56</cite></blockquote>



<p>Seems a clear condemnation of the so-called &#8220;crime&#8221; of non-belief.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-the-punishment-of-those-who-wage-war-against-allah-and-his-messenger-and-strive-to-make-mischief-in-the-land-is-only-this-that-they-should-be-murdered-or-crucified-or-their-hands-and-their-feet-should-be-cut-off-on-opposite-sides-or-they-should-be-imprisoned-this-shall-be-as-a-disgrace-for-them-in-this-world-and-in-the-hereafter-they-shall-have-a-grievous-chastisement"><em>The punishment of those who wage war against Allah and His messenger and strive to make mischief in the land is only this, that they should be murdered or crucified or their hands and their feet should be cut off on opposite sides or they should be imprisoned; this shall be as a disgrace for them in this world, and in the hereafter, they shall have a grievous chastisement</em></p>
<cite>Quran 5:33</cite></blockquote>



<p>And then there is this:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-remember-when-your-lord-inspired-the-angels-i-will-cast-terror-into-the-hearts-of-those-who-disbelieve-therefore-strike-off-their-heads-and-strike-off-every-fingertip-of-them"><em>&#8220;(Remember) when your Lord inspired the angels&#8230; &#8220;I will cast terror into the hearts of those who disbelieve. Therefore, strike off their heads and strike off every fingertip of them&#8221;</em></p>
<cite>Quran 8:12</cite></blockquote>



<p>The Quran predates America and modern Western culture. So, in what sense did the West invent terrorism? The Quran was clearly advocating terrorism long before America or the modern Western world was.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-truth-is-that-islam-is-a-death-worshiping-cult-of-widespread-genocide">The truth is that Islam is a death-worshiping cult of widespread genocide. </h3>


<p>During the trial of Yousef, Judge Duffy did not morally condemn Islam for its death worship. He apologized for Islam and faith. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg" alt="Picture of Muhammad." class="wp-image-26299" width="320" height="380" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg 640w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires-253x300.jpg 253w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Islam does not allow anyone to draw its deranged, murderous Prophet. But <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_%22Prophet%22_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jason</a> has done just that.<br>Image available under the Creative Commons <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/deed.en" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Share-Alike License</a>.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Duffy did not condemn the sacrifice collection of such cults and religions. Duffy condemned the ego, the very Western values that had made the twin towers possible!</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-ramzi-yousef-you-claim-to-be-an-islamic-militant-of-all-the-persons-killed-or-harmed-in-some-way-by-the-world-trade-center-bomb-you-cannot-name-one-who-was-against-you-or-your-cause-you-did-not-care-just-so-long-as-you-left-dead-bodies-and-people-hurt">Ramzi Yousef, you claim to be an Islamic militant. Of all the persons killed or harmed in some way by the World Trade Center bomb, you cannot name one who was against you or your cause. You did not care, just so long as you left dead bodies and people hurt.</p>



<p id="htoc-ramzi-yousef-you-are-not-fit-to-uphold-islam-your-god-is-a-god-of-death-your-god-is-not-allah">Ramzi Yousef, you are not fit to uphold Islam. Your God is a god of death. Your God is not Allah&nbsp;&#8230;</p>



<p id="htoc-you-weren-t-seeking-conversions-the-only-thing-you-wanted-to-do-was-to-cause-death-your-god-is-not-allah-you-worship-death-and-destruction-what-you-do-you-do-not-for-allah-you-do-it-only-to-satisfy-your-twisted-sense-of-ego">You weren&#8217;t seeking conversions. The only thing you wanted to do was to cause death. Your God is not Allah. You worship death and destruction. What you do, you do not for Allah; you do it only to satisfy your twisted sense of ego.</p>



<p id="htoc-you-would-have-others-believe-that-you-are-a-soldier-but-the-attacks-on-civilization-for-which-you-stand-convicted-here-were-sneak-attacks-which-sought-to-kill-and-maim-totally-innocent-people">You would have others believe that you are a soldier, but the attacks on civilization for which you stand convicted here were sneak attacks which sought to kill and maim totally innocent people.</p>



<p id="htoc-you-ramzi-yousef-came-to-this-country-pretending-to-be-an-islamic-fundamentalist-but-you-cared-little-or-nothing-for-islam-or-the-faith-of-the-muslims-rather-you-adored-not-allah-but-the-evil-yourself-have-become-and-i-must-say-that-as-an-apostle-of-evil-you-have-been-most-effective-29">You, Ramzi Yousef, came to this country pretending to be an Islamic fundamentalist, but you cared little or nothing for Islam or the faith of the Muslims. Rather, you adored not Allah, but the evil yourself have become. And I must say that as an apostle of evil, you have been most effective. <sup><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramzi_Yousef#cite_note-FullExcerpt-29">[29]</a></sup></p>
<cite>Judge Duffy, Wikipedia</cite></blockquote>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-but-we-have-seen-that-according-to-the-quran-itself-yousef-was-acting-entirely-consistent-with-the-quran">But we have seen that according to the Quran itself, Yousef was acting entirely consistent with the Quran. </h3>


<p>The Quran has many verses like the ones given above. Not one of them says that a true Muslim shall spare heretic imprisonment or a violent death!</p>



<p>Yousef is acting just as the Quran, as Islam demands. Let us look at another quote:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-not-equal-are-those-of-the-believers-who-sit-at-home-except-those-who-are-disabled-by-injury-or-are-blind-or-lame-etc-and-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-in-the-cause-of-allah-with-their-wealth-and-their-lives-allah-has-preferred-in-grades-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-with-their-wealth-and-their-lives-above-those-who-sit-at-home-unto-each-allah-has-promised-good-paradise-but-allah-has-preferred-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-above-those-who-sit-at-home-by-a-huge-reward"><em>Not equal are those of the believers who sit (at home), except those who are disabled (by injury or are blind or lame, etc.), and those who strive hard and fight in the Cause of Allah with their wealth and their lives. Allah has preferred in grades those who strive hard and fight with their wealth and their lives above those who sit (at home). Unto each, Allah has promised good (Paradise), but Allah has preferred those who strive hard and fight, above those who sit (at home) by a huge reward &#8220;</em></p>
<cite>Quran 4:95</cite></blockquote>



<p>This verse clearly criticizes peaceful Muslims! It holds those willing to strike the nonbeliever as morally superior to those that refuse to do so!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="640" height="427" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion.jpg" alt="Nuclear mushroom cloud." class="wp-image-26298" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion.jpg 640w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">If Islamic nations, such as Iran, want wear with the US, we should give it to them&#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-september-11-2001-islam-attacks-again"><strong>September 11, 2001</strong> &#8212; Islam Attacks Again</h2>


<p>On September 11, 2001, the Western values of &#8220;life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness&#8221; were attacked again. This time, the Twin Towers collapsed. 2,192 civilians died and 414 sworn personnel died. &nbsp;</p>



<p>If only the West did not apologize for its values. If only America stood firmly and <a href="https://theobjectivestandard.com/2007/11/american-victory-over-japan-1945/?fbclid=IwAR11_faO6RxZnaEh-z5HwCehwF-XyEGnPkO1x5SLVbEvT-0c_5TFMtOz5Wk">morally behind its victory over Japan in 1945</a>. If only Judge Duffy and America had morally condemned Islamic ideologies as evil. If only&#8230;</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Absurdity of Faith</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 22:43:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=657</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this article, I am going to demonstrate that faith is by its very nature unreasonable and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="d19e">In this article, I am going to show that religious faith is unreasonable, and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. We can make very similar arguments about other kinds of faith. However, we will focus on religious faith.</p>


<h2 class="simpletoc-title">Table of Contents</h2>
<ol class="simpletoc-list">
<li><a href="#what-is-faith">What is Faith?</a></li>
<li><a href="#what-is-the-harm">What is the Harm?</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#justified-trust">Is Biblical Faith “Justified Trust”?</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#bible-quotes">Bible Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="4/#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li></ol>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-faith"><strong>What is Faith?</strong></h2>


<p id="63a2">I define faith as:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-the-blind-acceptance-of-assertions-in-the-absence-of-any-evidence-or-proof-based-on-the-emotional-desire-for-that-assertion-to-be-true"><em>The blind acceptance of assertions in the absence of any evidence or proof, based on the emotional desire for that assertion to be true.</em></p>
<cite>Dwayne Davies</cite></blockquote>



<p id="17ba">The only claims of any merit are those that help us achieve some good value or another. That value might be to understand how to deal with the world around you and stay alive. It might be how to get lots of money and buy that house you want. It could be any value that you might imagine. </p>



<p id="17ba">However, for a value and claim to be of worth, it must help us achieve some purpose based on reality. If not, of what use could it possibly be to anyone?</p>



<p>To achieve good values, we must deal with the world as it really is. We must understand how the world works and deal with reality as it is. Only the things that help us do this help us to achieve values. Therefore, in order to help us achieve values in the real world, a claim must have a valid relation to the world. It must have some relation to observable facts. If not, then it is impossible for it to have any merit. That which has no relation to the real world is useless in achieving values. </p>



<p>If we are going to make or evaluate claims about reality, the only ones that are of any use in achieving values are those that correspond with reality. Truth is correspondence with reality. Truth is that which corresponds to the way things are. Therefore, the only claim that has any merit is that which has some truth to it.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="500" height="419" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg" alt="Earth under a dome (the firmament)." class="wp-image-26326" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg 500w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Bible seems to think the Earth is flat and with a over it. Possibly with stars embedded into the dome. But we should not take its word for any of that, should we?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>But how do we know whether a claim is true? You must first establish the possibility of the claim. If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. If you make an assertion without evidence, we cannot show it to correspond to reality. That assertion is, therefore, entirely without merit.</p>



<p>How do we establish whether something is possible? We discuss that in <a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this article on possibility.</a> Indeed, we took much of this section from that article.</p>



<p>To summarize that article, before we take any claim seriously, we must first establish that there is some evidence that it might be true. Otherwise, it is a waste of time considering it. </p>



<p id="2b1f">If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. Why should anyone accept any claim in the absence of evidence? Why would anyone do this when it could have no objective value? </p>



<p>Because they want it to be true. They have no cognitive reason to want it to be true. That person simply feels that it is preferable for it to be true. They feel an emotional response to the assertions being made, which makes them want to believe that the assertion must be true. </p>



<p>There is no reason to accept something merely because you want it to be true. Emotions are not tools of cognition. A claim is not valid because you wish it to be so. </p>



<p>But that is what faith is, the acceptance of things for which there is no evidence or proof. Faith is, therefore, the acceptance of baseless assertions for no reason and because someone wants it to be true based on emotion. However, emotions are not a valid reason for believing something.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-the-harm">What is the Harm?</h2>


<p id="fba5">Faith and reality are always in conflict. So is virtually every claim accepted for no reason and defended against reason. Knowing the truth is not a trivial task. It requires careful observation of reality, serious thought and a dedication to understanding the facts for what they are. </p>



<p id="a0eb">Faith is the refusal to do any of that. Faith is the attempt to bypass thought and proceed directly to the truth by wishing empty assertions to be fact. As though wanting something to be true somehow makes it so.</p>



<p id="622c">Assertions accepted on faith are almost always wrong. There is no real chance that anything you believe for no reason corresponds to the facts. There is essentially no chance that your blind assertions are true.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg" alt="Eve presents Adam the apple in the snake's mouth." class="wp-image-26328" width="640" height="426" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg 640w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The story of Adam and Eve condemns man for having the knowledge of good and evil. Condemns man for seeking an understanding of the world&#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Which is why the Bible is almost invariably wrong about everything. It is wrong about the shape of the Earth, and when it asserts that pi is exactly three. It is wrong when it pretends that Earth has a glass dome above it that lets the rain in. There are lots of other silly examples like this.</p>



<p>Therefore, almost everything every religion says about the universe is wrong. That is why their cosmologies are always wrong. That is why, when religions say what is right or wrong, they are frequently wrong.</p>



<p>Many religions prohibit things like theft or murder, in certain circumstances. The Bible includes commandments not to steal or murder. Most of us would agree that these are objectively wrong. These are examples of the few instances of things in the Bible that reasonable people might agree with.</p>



<p>However, the Bible does not forbid murder because of any valid reasoning. It does not forbid killing people because of any real respect for individual rights. It does this because it asserts God would not like this for reasons that are not entirely clear.  It is the same with stealing, which is not forbidden because of any arguments to do with property rights, but again for reasons that God does not make clear.</p>



<p>So even when it forbids things that reasonable people might consider wrong, it does not do so for valid reasons. Religions forbid things for invalid reasons and manage to once again prove that they are wrong. </p>



<p id="f195">Once you have rejected reality and embraced faith, what does that leave you to believe? Whatever you want to believe in, as long as we assume it blindly.</p>



<p id="63fe">Most often, this takes the form of whatever is emotionally satisfying or seems superficially easy to grasp. Or which provides moral guidance with little to no actual connection to how man should act to be happy and thrive.</p>



<p id="0e6a">But just because something is easy to understand does not mean that it is true. Something like the theory of a flat Earth might seem intuitive. However, the Earth is not flat. </p>



<p>It seemed intuitive to the Greeks that there were no <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">irr</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">ational numbers</a>. However, they were wrong and irrational numbers turn up all the time in mathematics. </p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating Christ Interview with James Valliant</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 22:37:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Creating Christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Valliant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romans]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=645</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we interview James Valliant, author of the important book "Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors Invented Christianity". ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a republishing of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast interview with James Valliant, one of the authors of the book Creating Christ. We talk about this important book and what it reveals about the Roman origins of Christianity. </p>



<p>For those unaware, the Metaphysics of Physics was the previous incarnation of this site and for a time in included a podcast.</p>



<p>You can read the transcript or use the audio player below to listen to the interview. Or do both if you prefer!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><a href="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" data-type="URL" data-id="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the episode.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-introduction">Introduction</h2>


<p>Today we interview James Valliant, author of the important book &#8220;<a href="https://www.creatingchrist.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors Invented Christianity</a>&#8220;. This interview is basically a question-led interview and provides long answers to the relatively few questions which were required.</p>



<p>Please note that some of our interviews reference &#8220;Metaphysics of Physics&#8221;. This was the previous incarnation of the Rational Metaphysician.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-about-creating-christ">About Creating Christ</h2>


<p>The thesis of Creating Christ is that Christianity is the result of Roman propaganda in the first and second centuries. Designed to pacify Messianic Jews and to integrate them into Roman society.</p>



<p>This might not seem to be an important subject or a probable claim, but it really is. If Christianity and its proper place in the history of the West is to be understood, it is important that the true nature of Christianity is understood.</p>



<p>But, is this claim true? Yes, as you will discover when you listen to the podcast and or read the transcript.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist.jpg" alt="Cover of the Creating Christ book." class="wp-image-26420" width="263" height="394" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist.jpg 350w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /></figure></div>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-episode-transcript">Episode Transcript</h2>


<p>This episode is about one hour and fifty-six minutes long. As a result, we have not implemented the episode transcript in the usual form. We have provided a transcript in an edited and more formal form. It is much like a formal written answer to the question, however, the questions do very closely match the content of the audio.</p>



<p>However, please note that there may be minor mistakes in the transcript. I have done my best to clean up any spelling and grammatical errors, however, due to time constraints, it has not been possible to edit out all possibility of such.</p>



<p><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode_ten.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode_ten.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here to download the PDF transcript.</a></p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-brief-excerpt">Brief Excerpt</h2>


<p><strong>Ashna: James, please introduce yourself and explain the thesis of the book:</strong></p>



<p><strong>James:</strong> My name is James Valliant. I am the co-author of the new book &#8220;Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors invented Christianity&#8221;.<br><br>Basically, it takes on what would certainly strike most people today, certainly most Christians today, as a rather outrageous thesis. That in fact, the New Testament is Roman propaganda. That when it was originally written, it was written with a certain political agenda. As well as a certain theological agenda.</p>



<p>Most Christians would think that is crazy. They regard Christianity as the very opposite of Roman philosophy. They believe that the Romans persecuted Christianity. Hollywood has certainly convinced them that in the last century. But, there&#8217;s a forgotten history here.</p>



<p>Two thousand years ago, there was cataclysmic war between the Roman Empire and Jewish Messianic rebels. And the rebellion was largely motivated by religious factors. It was that war, that cataclysmic war, that destroyed the temple, for example. Reduced it to the Wailing Wall that it is today.</p>



<p>It is difficult for me to imagine that Christianity emerging at that very same moment in history is just an accident. And when we started our research, we found nothing to contradict our theory. And then we found some remarkable physical evidence which basically demonstrated it.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="237" height="240" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda.jpg" alt="Roman coin." class="wp-image-26421" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda.jpg 237w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 237px) 100vw, 237px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Like many Roman coins were, Christianity is naked Roman propaganda.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In short, the thesis is that what we have in the New Testament is Roman propaganda written 2000 years ago to quell the Jewish revolt. That is very much the 30,000-foot level of analysis. Or I should say 10,000-meter level, from New Zealand. [footnote]Dwayne and Ashna were living in New Zealand when this was recorded[/footnote]</p>



<p>So, from way up in the sky, looking down on it, the way to really look at it is that the moral idealism that we read in the New Testament is really a form of political propaganda.</p>



<p>It is also regarded as moral idealism, both by Christians and even by secular people who have adopted it.</p>



<p>And having forgotten the original context of the New Testament&#8217;s creation, it&#8217;s very easy to detach ourselves from that. And to think of the doctrine of Jesus Christ as sort of an unworldly, non-earthly form of moral idealism.</p>



<p>But when you just change the angle slightly and you look at the entire New Testament from this new angle, suddenly everything is explained. We were simply blown away, I think when we started pulling that string because nothing contradicted it. And all the evidence seemed to confirm it.</p>



<p><strong>Ashna: Does it matter how Christianity got started? Why does that matter to us now?</strong></p>



<p><strong>James:</strong> Well, that&#8217;s a fair question. This is 2000-year-old history and Christianity has certainly changed considerably. At least it&#8217;s operative doctrines have. The New Testament itself obviously has not changed, but the way Christians understand and live those doctrines has dramatically changed over the last 2000 years.</p>



<p>So that&#8217;s a very good question. Why should we even care? Well, there are two very good answers to that. History matters. And particularly the history of ideas.</p>



<p>Human beings are really motivated by their ideas and their history can be understood in terms of the power of ideas. Although these ideas are 2000 years old, they literally reach across the millennia and control our psychologies, our view of what&#8217;s morally right and wrong.</p>



<p>Even people who are secular, people who tend to be on political left and who don&#8217;t have much of a religion, have basically adopted Christian social ethics is their own. Socialists and Communists have basically applied the ethics and the social doctrine of the New Testament in a very consistentway. While simply leaving out all the mystical and miraculous stuff.</p>



<p>So, the values and the ideas expressed in the New Testament are still a living vital, powerful force. On the American left, they have adopted elements of pacifism, social altruism and concern for the poor above other considerations.</p>



<p>The discovery, whether you&#8217;re religious or not, that the moral idealism of Christianity is in fact simply a form of political propaganda, is crucially important.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" length="73837935" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating Christ Archaeology with Warren Fahy</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/creating-christ-archaeology-warren-fahy/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/creating-christ-archaeology-warren-fahy/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 22:37:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christainity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Creating Christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[God]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=643</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, the co-author of Creating Christ. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a republishing of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast interview with Warren Fahy, one of the authors of Creating Christ.  We discuss the archeology of Creating Christ as well as some other arguments for the thesis presented in the book.</p>



<p>For those unaware, the Metaphysics of Physics was the previous incarnation of this site and for a time in included a podcast.</p>



<p>You can read the transcript or use the audio player below to listen to the interview. Or do both if you prefer!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/MOP-2019-07-14-creating-christ-archaeology-with-warren-fahy.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://moppodcast.azureedge.net/podcasts/MOP-12018-12-12-interview-with-physicist-juanma.mp3" target="_blank">Clic</a><a href="https://moppodcast.azureedge.net/podcasts/MOP-12018-12-12-interview-with-physicist-juanma.mp3">k</a><a href="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/MOP-2019-07-14-creating-christ-archaeology-with-warren-fahy.mp3" data-type="URL" data-id="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/MOP-2019-07-14-creating-christ-archaeology-with-warren-fahy.mp3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> here</a> to download the episode.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-introduction">Introduction</h2>


<p>Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, the co-author of Creating Christ. We have talked about Creating Christ before, when we interviewed the books of the other author, James Valliant. You can find that interview <a href="http://localhost/rational/interview-creating-christ-author/" data-type="post" data-id="645" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. You can find out more about the <a href="https://www.creatingchrist.com/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.creatingchrist.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">book here</a>.</p>



<p>Today we are focusing on the archeology of Creating Christ, although we will cover a few other issues as well. We cover some stuff that is not covered so much or at all in our previous Creating Christ interview. Meaning that you should definitely listen to this one, even if you have listened to the other one. Or should that be, especially if you have listened to the other one?</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-what-is-creating-christ">What is Creating Christ?</h2>


<p>What is Creating Christ? Some of you may not know. It is a book that shows the Roman origins of Christianity. Not simply the fact that the Roman Empire morphed into the Catholic Church, but the thesis that the Romans created the religion!</p>



<p>It might sound radical, but the book makes a very compelling case for how this must be true. If you have not read it, you really should. You can get it from Amazon.</p>



<p>You really should listen to that interview first, as it gives a really in depth coverage of the book. Or, you can read the book first.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist-1.jpg" alt="The cover of the Creating Christ book." class="wp-image-26458" width="263" height="394" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist-1.jpg 350w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist-1-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /></figure></div>


<p>Please note that the Amazon Kindle edition is currently not available. As far as I can tell, this may be due to some disgruntled customer complaining about the book&#8217;s technical issues. Which I can assure, having owning a copy of it in Kindle, do not exist!</p>



<p>Apparently, one customer complaint can cause items to go under review and be taken off the Kindle marketplace. If so, this policy should change!</p>



<p>I have given them some polite feedback on this. You can too, if you want. But, please be civil. Incivility helps nobody, least of all Creating Christ or its fantastic authors!</p>



<p>We have not presented the transcript of this in web page form. Instead, you can listen to the audio or download the PDF transcript.</p>



<p>However, there may be mistakes in the transcript. Any mistakes in transcription represent our own errors or a transcription error we missed.</p>



<p><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode24.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode24.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the PDF transcript.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-a-brief-excerpt">A Brief Excerpt</h2>


<p><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Do you and/or James have any of the coins from the book? Or more likely, replicas.<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> It’s amazing how readily available those coins are. I don’t have one. But I got a Vespasian coin for James several years ago. And it was like 50 cents at a convention.<br><br>The Flavian minted millions and millions of coins and they&#8217;re still quite available.<br><br>And so, I don&#8217;t. Someday I would love to have a fish and anchor Titus coin. That is certainly something I will obtain at some point.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> In the book, we see that the cross was not the first primary symbol used by early Christians. Tell us about some of the earliest symbols they used.<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> Well, if you go back to the very first catacombs, the very first evidence of archaeological evidence of Christianity, what you&#8217;ll find is that the symbols they were using were not the Cross.<br><br>They were using the anchor, either flanked by fish or wrapped around by a fish. And so, these are the earliest symbols of Christianity that we know. And it wasn&#8217;t until about two or three centuries later, when Constantine<br>instated Christianity as the official religion of the Roman Empire, that he switched the symbol to the Cross.<br><br>He did so because he had seen a cross in the sky during a battle. And as he saw that vision, it turned the tide of the battle and he won the battle. And so, he decided to instate the cross is a symbol of Christianity.</p>



<p>His mother traveled to the Holy Land. And as legend has it, brought back a piece of the original cross. And that was all part of the propaganda that instituted this new symbolism.<br><br>But before that, the fish and anchor that was the predominant symbol of<br>Christianity. And it was also the symbol used by the Flavian Emperors<br>Titus and very briefly his brother Domitian.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Tell us about the mosaic we see on the front cover of the newest editions of the book.<br><br><strong>Warren: </strong>Yes. Well, that, of course, was buried by the eruption of Mount Vesuvius in Herculaneum. Only two months after Emperor Titus seceded his father as emperor of Rome.<br><br>And it was an amazing find because it was almost like a legend for the symbolism used by the Christians.<br><br>Of course, there is no archaeological evidence from the first century of Christianity that has been recognized as evidence of Christianity.<br><br>So, this predated by decades, the first catacombs in which Titus’ own niece was buried. And that symbol that was on his coins, of the dolphin wrapped around an anchor, is echoed throughout those earliest Christians catacombs.<br><br>So, this symbol, this particular mosaic, was on the bottom of a pool in a gymnasium in Herculaneum. One that had originally been built by Emperor Augustus.<br><br>It was an imperial gymnasium that would have been under the care of the Flavians for decades. Because before then, Vespasian, the father of Titus had also a Flavian Emperor for 19 years.<br><br>There were always earthquakes going on in Herculaneum, because it was right next to the active volcano, Vesuvius. And so, they were constantly having to repair the bottom of pools. Because they would crack and then the water would leak out.And at the time of the eruption, there were two pools in this gymnasium.<br><br>One of which had been drained in order to effect repairs on the cracked bottom of the pool.<br><br>The other one that had this mosaic was filled, indicating that had been recently refurbished. So that would have been refurbished by the Flavians certainly.<br><br>And here they are using this symbol, which is reflected also on Titus’ coins. Where you see an anchor flanked by two dolphins. And two people swimming towards the anchor.<br><br>Exactly the sort of thing you would see in Christian catacombs for the next two or three centuries. And yet it predates Christian use of the symbol by decades.<br><br>That was astonishing. When I first found it, I called James. I think it was at 3:30 in the morning when I came across it. I was absolutely flabbergasted to see what that pool indicated.<br><br>At that point, probably nobody on earth knew exactly what an amazing find that mosaic was in terms of historical significance.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Which artefacts show us some of the religious syncretism going on with the figure of Christ?<br><br>I believe, for instance, that there is a depiction of Alexander the Great as Helios that seems to have inspired depictions of Jesus.<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> Yes, there are. There are plenty. Of course, the mystery cults of the pagan world, the Hellenistic world, are combined with the Christian concept of the Messiah. In a way that&#8217;s undeniable.<br><br>From Dionysius to Apollo, to the Sun God. All these pagan elements are combined within the idea of the Messiah. But the Jewish people would never have incorporated these into the idea of the Messiah. They had to have come from the pagan world.<br><br>And we can see those. Hercules dies and is resurrected and Dionysius is. Osiris dies and is resurrected. That is a very common thing.<br><br>And Mithra was born on December 25, in a manger visited by three wise men, three Magi, from the East that followed a star.<br><br>That all predated Christianity, but hundreds of years. And yet here it is in Christianity.So yes, there are lots and lots of different pagan influences in the syncretic conception of Jesus Christ.</p>



<p><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Why was the Sun God shown on a coin of Titus?<br><br><strong>Warren: </strong>Yeah, very good question.<br><br>Sol was a sun god and came from the East. And of course, the sun rises in the east. And he was associated with Apollo.</p>



<p>Apollo is a healer god. And Jesus is a healer god. He also rises from the East, in Judea. Just as Titus and Vespasian made their bones, so to speak, in their campaigns in Judea, to the east of Rome.<br><br>And so, they came from the East and rose to the throne of Rome, by their exploits in the East. So, the idea of a sun god, was convenient for Titus to use on his coins.<br></p>



<p>Also, the Flavians were seen as healers of Rome. Because they had just gone through a giant civil war. And the fire of Rome had devastated 70% of the city of Rome.<br><br>And then, of course, the Jewish war was a giant war of secession. A civil war between who is going to replace Nero after he died.<br><br>And so, this was a huge tumultuous time of history for Rome. And the Flavians saw themselves as healers who are going to now repair all the damage that had been done in the last couple of decades in Rome.<br><br>So that was a very convenient way for Titus to associate himself with Sol and with Apollo, these Eastern healer gods.<br><br><strong>Dwayne: </strong>We see the anchor symbol used by early Christians on Flavian tombs. Now, isn&#8217;t that interesting?<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> Oh, yes, I mean it well, it&#8217;s absolutely astonishing. Because why would Christians be using symbols that were employed by the Flavius on their coins and on mosaics?<br><br>For instance, the one in Herculaneum. And on architectural details in, for instance, a temple of Venus that the Flavians built. And also, in the Coliseum, which the Flavians built. The Colosseum was originally called the Flavian Amphitheatre.<br><br>And so, all of these symbols are being employed by the Emperors of Rome. Even in the Coliseum where Christians were supposedly thrown to the lions.According to commonly accepted history, this is clearly a very inexplicable, parallel between the two groups. How could Christians be using Imperial symbols used in the Coliseum itself only a few miles away from their catacombs?<br><br>It implies that there was certainly some kind of a relationship between the Flavian dynasty, the Flavian emperors and Christianity. And there&#8217;s ally no way around it.<br><br>There were so many different symbols that the Christians could have chosen. Certainly, ones that were not pagan, right?<br><br>Considering that it was supposed to have been a homegrown religion that came from Judea. One which would have already had great prescriptions from using pagan symbolism. Especially ones that that denoted a Roman pagan god like Apollo. Which is the symbol of dolphin, a symbol of Apollo.<br><br>The Jews would never have allowed that to be on their coins. In fact, they had elaborate money changing setup just so that people would ever donate coins with that kind of symbolism to the temple in Jerusalem.<br><br>So yes, we have the fact that the Christians earliest symbols are the symbols that Emperor Titus used. The fact that they used the same symbols used throughout their archaeology, coins and mosaics, and so forth, is a profound problem for the traditional view of a huge conflict between the Roman emperors and the Christians</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/creating-christ-archaeology-warren-fahy/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://moppodcast.azureedge.net/podcasts/MOP-12018-12-12-interview-with-physicist-juanma.mp3" length="30773782" type="audio/mpeg" />
<enclosure url="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/MOP-2019-07-14-creating-christ-archaeology-with-warren-fahy.mp3" length="16155672" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Possible and the Impossible</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 02:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[impossible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=35</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we are exploring the concept of "possible" and "impossible". What does it mean for something to be possible or impossible?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today, we are exploring the concepts of the &#8220;possible&#8221; and &#8220;impossible&#8221; and their important role in cognition, particularly in the sciences.</p>


<h2 class="simpletoc-title">Table of Contents</h2>
<ol class="simpletoc-list" style="padding-left:0;list-style:none;">
<li><a href="#the-possible">The Possible</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="#htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-just-because-a-claim-is-true-does-not-mean-it-is-possible-in-the-absence-of-evidence">Just because a claim is true does not mean you have established that it is  true or possible in the absence of evidence.</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><a href="2/#what-counts-as-evidence">What Counts as Evidence?</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#the-impossible">The Impossible</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="2/#htoc-if-you-can-establish-if-x-was-true-it-would-contradict-a-known-fact-then-x-cannot-be-possible">If you can establish that if X was true, it would contradict a known fact, then X cannot be possible.</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#htoc-that-which-contradicts-with-any-known-fact-of-reality-is-impossible">That which contradicts any known fact of reality is impossible.</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><a href="3/#why-does-this-matter">Why Does this Matter?</a></li></ol>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-possible">The Possible</h2>


<p>We must first establish the proper meaning of “possible”. I think many people, including many in science, do not grasp the meaning of this concept. Even though it is an important concept in science and all other spheres of thought.</p>



<p>Here is the definition of possible that I am using in this article:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-relating-to-a-claim-for-which-there-is-some-evidence-for-a-claim-is-possible-if-some-evidence-exists-to-support-it-being-true-and-there-is-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">Relating to a claim for which there is some evidence for. A claim is possible if some evidence exists to support it being true and there is none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it. </h3>


<p>The claim does not have to be proven true, there simply needs to be some evidence in favor of it. I consider a theory which is proven possible as it meets the above criteria. </p>



<p>In order to take any claim seriously, you should first establish that the claim is at least possible. There must be some amount of evidence that supports the claim. There must be a reason that the claim is potentially true. That the claim being made matches the fact of reality.  If you cannot do this, then your claim is arbitrary. There is no way to connect it back to reality of any kind.</p>



<p>Something is not “possible” simply because one cannot think why it is not true. One has to have a reason we should consider it to be true.</p>



<p>“X is possible” means: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-that-according-to-the-context-of-my-knowledge-there-is-some-evidence-that-x-is-true-and-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">That according to the context of my knowledge, there is some evidence that X is true and none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Note that there may not be very <em>much</em> evidence that supports X, but there must be at least some evidence.</p>



<p>The evidence might not be very conclusive, and the truth of X may still need to be verified. Tt least I have established the <em>possibility</em> of the claim. At least I have established some reason to believe that the claim might be valid.</p>



<p>Let’s take an example.</p>



<p>I wonder if humans might have evolved via a process of natural selection from some other species. I have not yet established that this is possible. It is just speculation. That I have guessed that this might be the case is not the same as establishing that it is possible. A guess in the absence of evidence does not establish that something is possible.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="416" height="480" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg" alt="Chimpanzee." class="wp-image-26305" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg 416w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy-260x300.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hey, seems plausible to me, this chimp looks like many people I know &#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>So, I then try to find evidence that would suggest such a thing. What kind of evidence might show this? I could look for evidence that ancient apes had primitive versions of some features humans have and that over time, later species of apes developed versions of these features that are ever closer to the version of those features shared by humans.</p>



<p>For instance, I could look at the skull of some very ancient apes. I might notice that these skulls have brain cases larger than some of their earlier relatives. These brain cases are larger than some other human relatives. However, their brain cases are not as large as the brain cases possessed by human skulls. I may then notice that later species of apes have still larger brain cases. And later generations have still larger brain cases than that. </p>



<p>And so on, so that the closer these species get to humans in time, the larger the brain cases possessed by these apes and the more human like their brain cases are. </p>



<p>What would this show? It suggests that as time progresses, that the successive species of apes are becoming more and more like humans in terms of their brain cases. We can say the same about other skeletal structures and parts of their genome! We can show that over time, we see apes that are developing increasingly human-like pelvises, for instance.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="256" height="258" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg" alt="Skull of an ancient pre-human ape." class="wp-image-26308" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg 256w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-150x150.jpg 150w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">There is much evidence that man evolved from other apes. Evidence such as this Australopithecus skull.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Therefore, it seems possible that man evolved from an ape! I have not simply asserted that it is so because I imagine it is so. I have concluded that it might be so, based on some evidence that seems to suggest this.</p>



<p>Am I certain of this? No, I might not be. I might think that this is not very conclusive yet. However, I have some reason, based on evidence, to think that it might be true. I have a <em>basis</em> for my belief that man evolved from these earlier species of apes.</p>



<p>Of course, in the modern age, we have now proven beyond all rational doubt humans did indeed evolve from other apes and that humans are still apes! We have so much evidence for this that it would be perverse to suggest that we did not evolve from apes. Sadly, this does not stop millions of Creationists from asserting that we did not evolve from apes. </p>



<p>However, suppose that I simply declare that man evolved from apes. Suppose that I have no evidence of any kind to suggest that this is true. I just assert that it is so because I simply believe it to be so, based on faith.</p>



<p>This is speculation. It is not the same as establishing that something is possible. You have no reason, no evidence, to believe it might be true. One cannot base an argument solely on speculation. Then you have simply asserted it on faith.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
