<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>proof &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/proof/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Rational Nonfiction Author</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 18:46:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cropped-Ashna-Dwaynes-Wedding-23-crop-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>proof &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Absurdity of Faith</title>
		<link>/the-absurdity-of-faith/</link>
					<comments>/the-absurdity-of-faith/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 22:43:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=657</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this article, I am going to demonstrate that faith is by its very nature unreasonable and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="d19e">In this article, I am going to show that religious faith is unreasonable, and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. We can make very similar arguments about other kinds of faith. However, we will focus on religious faith.</p>





<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-faith"><strong>What is Faith?</strong></h2>



<p id="63a2">I define faith as:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-the-blind-acceptance-of-assertions-in-the-absence-of-any-evidence-or-proof-based-on-the-emotional-desire-for-that-assertion-to-be-true"><em>The blind acceptance of assertions in the absence of any evidence or proof, based on the emotional desire for that assertion to be true.</em></p>
<cite>Dwayne Davies</cite></blockquote>



<p id="17ba">The only claims of any merit are those that help us achieve some good value or another. That value might be to understand how to deal with the world around you and stay alive. It might be how to get lots of money and buy that house you want. It could be any value that you might imagine. </p>



<p id="17ba">However, for a value and claim to be of worth, it must help us achieve some purpose based on reality. If not, of what use could it possibly be to anyone?</p>



<p>To achieve good values, we must deal with the world as it really is. We must understand how the world works and deal with reality as it is. Only the things that help us do this help us to achieve values. Therefore, in order to help us achieve values in the real world, a claim must have a valid relation to the world. It must have some relation to observable facts. If not, then it is impossible for it to have any merit. That which has no relation to the real world is useless in achieving values. </p>



<p>If we are going to make or evaluate claims about reality, the only ones that are of any use in achieving values are those that correspond with reality. Truth is correspondence with reality. Truth is that which corresponds to the way things are. Therefore, the only claim that has any merit is that which has some truth to it.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img  decoding="async" width="500" height="419"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg"  alt="Earth under a dome (the firmament)." class="wp-image-26326" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg 500w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Bible seems to think the Earth is flat and with a over it. Possibly with stars embedded into the dome. But we should not take its word for any of that, should we?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>But how do we know whether a claim is true? You must first establish the possibility of the claim. If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. If you make an assertion without evidence, we cannot show it to correspond to reality. That assertion is, therefore, entirely without merit.</p>



<p>How do we establish whether something is possible? We discuss that in <a href="/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="URL" data-id="/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this article on possibility.</a> Indeed, we took much of this section from that article.</p>



<p>To summarize that article, before we take any claim seriously, we must first establish that there is some evidence that it might be true. Otherwise, it is a waste of time considering it. </p>



<p id="2b1f">If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. Why should anyone accept any claim in the absence of evidence? Why would anyone do this when it could have no objective value? </p>



<p>Because they want it to be true. They have no cognitive reason to want it to be true. That person simply feels that it is preferable for it to be true. They feel an emotional response to the assertions being made, which makes them want to believe that the assertion must be true. </p>



<p>There is no reason to accept something merely because you want it to be true. Emotions are not tools of cognition. A claim is not valid because you wish it to be so. </p>



<p>But that is what faith is, the acceptance of things for which there is no evidence or proof. Faith is, therefore, the acceptance of baseless assertions for no reason and because someone wants it to be true based on emotion. However, emotions are not a valid reason for believing something.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-the-harm">What is the Harm?</h2>



<p id="fba5">Faith and reality are always in conflict. So is virtually every claim accepted for no reason and defended against reason. Knowing the truth is not a trivial task. It requires careful observation of reality, serious thought and a dedication to understanding the facts for what they are. </p>



<p id="a0eb">Faith is the refusal to do any of that. Faith is the attempt to bypass thought and proceed directly to the truth by wishing empty assertions to be fact. As though wanting something to be true somehow makes it so.</p>



<p id="622c">Assertions accepted on faith are almost always wrong. There is no real chance that anything you believe for no reason corresponds to the facts. There is essentially no chance that your blind assertions are true.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img  decoding="async"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg"  alt="Eve presents Adam the apple in the snake's mouth." class="wp-image-26328" width="640" height="426" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg 640w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The story of Adam and Eve condemns man for having the knowledge of good and evil. Condemns man for seeking an understanding of the world&#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Which is why the Bible is almost invariably wrong about everything. It is wrong about the shape of the Earth, and when it asserts that pi is exactly three. It is wrong when it pretends that Earth has a glass dome above it that lets the rain in. There are lots of other silly examples like this.</p>



<p>Therefore, almost everything every religion says about the universe is wrong. That is why their cosmologies are always wrong. That is why, when religions say what is right or wrong, they are frequently wrong.</p>



<p>Many religions prohibit things like theft or murder, in certain circumstances. The Bible includes commandments not to steal or murder. Most of us would agree that these are objectively wrong. These are examples of the few instances of things in the Bible that reasonable people might agree with.</p>



<p>However, the Bible does not forbid murder because of any valid reasoning. It does not forbid killing people because of any real respect for individual rights. It does this because it asserts God would not like this for reasons that are not entirely clear.  It is the same with stealing, which is not forbidden because of any arguments to do with property rights, but again for reasons that God does not make clear.</p>



<p>So even when it forbids things that reasonable people might consider wrong, it does not do so for valid reasons. Religions forbid things for invalid reasons and manage to once again prove that they are wrong. </p>



<p id="f195">Once you have rejected reality and embraced faith, what does that leave you to believe? Whatever you want to believe in, as long as we assume it blindly.</p>



<p id="63fe">Most often, this takes the form of whatever is emotionally satisfying or seems superficially easy to grasp. Or which provides moral guidance with little to no actual connection to how man should act to be happy and thrive.</p>



<p id="0e6a">But just because something is easy to understand does not mean that it is true. Something like the theory of a flat Earth might seem intuitive. However, the Earth is not flat. </p>



<p>It seemed intuitive to the Greeks that there were no <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">irr</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">ational numbers</a>. However, they were wrong and irrational numbers turn up all the time in mathematics. </p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-absurdity-of-faith/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Possible and the Impossible</title>
		<link>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/</link>
					<comments>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 02:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[impossible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=35</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we are exploring the concept of "possible" and "impossible". What does it mean for something to be possible or impossible?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today, we are exploring the concepts of the &#8220;possible&#8221; and &#8220;impossible&#8221; and their important role in cognition, particularly in the sciences.</p>





<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-possible">The Possible</h2>



<p>We must first establish the proper meaning of “possible”. I think many people, including many in science, do not grasp the meaning of this concept. Even though it is an important concept in science and all other spheres of thought.</p>



<p>Here is the definition of possible that I am using in this article:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-relating-to-a-claim-for-which-there-is-some-evidence-for-a-claim-is-possible-if-some-evidence-exists-to-support-it-being-true-and-there-is-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">Relating to a claim for which there is some evidence for. A claim is possible if some evidence exists to support it being true and there is none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it. </h3>



<p>The claim does not have to be proven true, there simply needs to be some evidence in favor of it. I consider a theory which is proven possible as it meets the above criteria. </p>



<p>In order to take any claim seriously, you should first establish that the claim is at least possible. There must be some amount of evidence that supports the claim. There must be a reason that the claim is potentially true. That the claim being made matches the fact of reality.  If you cannot do this, then your claim is arbitrary. There is no way to connect it back to reality of any kind.</p>



<p>Something is not “possible” simply because one cannot think why it is not true. One has to have a reason we should consider it to be true.</p>



<p>“X is possible” means: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-that-according-to-the-context-of-my-knowledge-there-is-some-evidence-that-x-is-true-and-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">That according to the context of my knowledge, there is some evidence that X is true and none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Note that there may not be very <em>much</em> evidence that supports X, but there must be at least some evidence.</p>



<p>The evidence might not be very conclusive, and the truth of X may still need to be verified. Tt least I have established the <em>possibility</em> of the claim. At least I have established some reason to believe that the claim might be valid.</p>



<p>Let’s take an example.</p>



<p>I wonder if humans might have evolved via a process of natural selection from some other species. I have not yet established that this is possible. It is just speculation. That I have guessed that this might be the case is not the same as establishing that it is possible. A guess in the absence of evidence does not establish that something is possible.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img  decoding="async" width="416" height="480"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg"  alt="Chimpanzee." class="wp-image-26305" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg 416w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy-260x300.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hey, seems plausible to me, this chimp looks like many people I know &#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>So, I then try to find evidence that would suggest such a thing. What kind of evidence might show this? I could look for evidence that ancient apes had primitive versions of some features humans have and that over time, later species of apes developed versions of these features that are ever closer to the version of those features shared by humans.</p>



<p>For instance, I could look at the skull of some very ancient apes. I might notice that these skulls have brain cases larger than some of their earlier relatives. These brain cases are larger than some other human relatives. However, their brain cases are not as large as the brain cases possessed by human skulls. I may then notice that later species of apes have still larger brain cases. And later generations have still larger brain cases than that. </p>



<p>And so on, so that the closer these species get to humans in time, the larger the brain cases possessed by these apes and the more human like their brain cases are. </p>



<p>What would this show? It suggests that as time progresses, that the successive species of apes are becoming more and more like humans in terms of their brain cases. We can say the same about other skeletal structures and parts of their genome! We can show that over time, we see apes that are developing increasingly human-like pelvises, for instance.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="256" height="258"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"  alt="Skull of an ancient pre-human ape." class="wp-image-26308" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg 256w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">There is much evidence that man evolved from other apes. Evidence such as this Australopithecus skull.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Therefore, it seems possible that man evolved from an ape! I have not simply asserted that it is so because I imagine it is so. I have concluded that it might be so, based on some evidence that seems to suggest this.</p>



<p>Am I certain of this? No, I might not be. I might think that this is not very conclusive yet. However, I have some reason, based on evidence, to think that it might be true. I have a <em>basis</em> for my belief that man evolved from these earlier species of apes.</p>



<p>Of course, in the modern age, we have now proven beyond all rational doubt humans did indeed evolve from other apes and that humans are still apes! We have so much evidence for this that it would be perverse to suggest that we did not evolve from apes. Sadly, this does not stop millions of Creationists from asserting that we did not evolve from apes. </p>



<p>However, suppose that I simply declare that man evolved from apes. Suppose that I have no evidence of any kind to suggest that this is true. I just assert that it is so because I simply believe it to be so, based on faith.</p>



<p>This is speculation. It is not the same as establishing that something is possible. You have no reason, no evidence, to believe it might be true. One cannot base an argument solely on speculation. Then you have simply asserted it on faith.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is &#8220;Settled Science&#8221; Scientific?</title>
		<link>/is-settled-science-scientific/</link>
					<comments>/is-settled-science-scientific/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 09:59:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hume]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knowledge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[logic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quote4s]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://metaphysicsofphysics.com/?p=20906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some people, including alleged champions of reason and science think that there is no such thing as settled science. Let's bust that unscientific nonsense.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Is there any such thing as settled science? I am going to argue that there is.</p>



<p>What do I mean by &#8220;settled&#8221; science? A scientific claim that any rational person would accept as true and established beyond any reasonable doubt. We do not expect such theories to be replaced by an alternate theory.</p>



<p>You might object that this is not very scientific! We must always keep in mind that we might be wrong. We need to be ready to adjust what we know to accommodate new information that might cast what we know today into doubt. Keep in mind that we are fallible and that we might come to invalid conclusions.</p>



<p>All knowledge, including science, is contextual. We study reality and, based on what we observe, we form logical conclusions. But we can only account for that we know about.</p>



<p>For instance, take Newtonian gravity. In the context of not knowing what happens near the speed of light, it was entirely reasonable to accept Newton&#8217;s laws of gravity as settled science. We did not know what happened at extremely high velocities, so we had no reason to doubt Newtonian gravity. Newtonian gravity is valid, within the context of things not moving close to the speed of light. </p>



<p>We then expanded our context to account for things near light speed. We realized that in that context, Einstein’s relativity provides better mathematics for what happens with gravity at near light speed. Does that mean that we had no reason to be certain about Newtonian gravity? </p>



<p>No, it does not. We knew it was an accurate description of gravity at speeds much lower than the speed of light.</p>



<p>That is why NASA uses Newtonian gravity for most purposes, even though relativistic equations would be more accurate. Newtonian gravity is easier to deal with and is extremely accurate at the speeds NASA works with.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="500" height="559"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg"  alt="Space shuttle launch." class="wp-image-26162" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg 500w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch-268x300.jpg 268w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">You may have noticed rockets do not go at anything near the speed of light. So, Newton&#8217;s gravity equations will work just fine thanks.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Certainty is contextual. Suppose, in the context of our knowledge, the available evidence supports a theory. We should be certain about that theory. But what we are wrong? After all, we used to believe some strange things.</p>



<p>We used to think things burned because of phlogiston. Phlogiston was a mysterious substance that was thought to exist in all combustible bodies.</p>



<p>We used to think that dinosaurs were all sluggish, scaly critters that probably lived in swamps to support their massive weight.</p>



<p>Yes, sometimes we are wrong. Sometimes the facts do not support our theories. There are some theories that we have no business accepting as anything more than a plausible hypothesis.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">These are the theories that do not make up the body of settled science. These are the theories we should not consider settled. </h3>



<p>It would be dishonest to consider a theory settled in the absence of evidence. It would also be dishonest to consider a theory settled if we did not understand it well enough to be sure it was consistent with all the available evidence.</p>



<p>Some theories are entirely reasonable within the context of the available evidence. Sometimes all the known evidence points to these theories being true. </p>



<p>Sometimes we understand the theory well enough to conclude it is entirely consistent with the facts. If the facts are consistent with that theory and only that theory, then we can be certain that the theory in question is true.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We should not entertain serious doubts about theories that have substantial evidence behind them. </h3>



<p>We can always <em>imagine</em> that we might disprove some theories. However, we should be certain about a theory if all the available evidence points to it being true.</p>



<p>Certainty does not require us to account for, by magic, for the possibility of a context of knowledge we do not currently possess. We can be certain that something is true even if there is something we do not know about now that may later show that it is not true.</p>



<p>Certainty is contextual, it is valid to be certain based on the context of available evidence. Provided that we are willing to address any evidence that arises, should the context of our knowledge change. We can be certain something is true. And yet adjust our theories when the context of our knowledge expands.</p>



<p>However, there are theories that we can consider completely and forever settled. These are theories we know with certainty and can prove with no shadow of a doubt to be true.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We know these facts are true and that we cannot show them to be false.</h3>



<p>It would contradict known facts of reality if they were not true. Things would have to not be what we know they are.</p>



<p>Examples of these would be that atoms exist. We know atoms exist; we have seen them. If they did not exist, almost everything we know about chemistry and atomic physics would not be true.</p>



<p>We know evolution happens. We might not know everything about how it happens, but we know it does. If I wanted disprove evolution, we would have to invalidate almost everything we know about biology and the known facts of biology would have to be other than what they are.</p>



<p>We know the Earth is round and that it orbits the Sun. To invalidate this, the direct evidence of our senses would have to be wrong! That we can see that the Earth is round would have to be fake. And how would we explain the observed behavior of Earth if it does not orbit the Sun? </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="450" height="450"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg"  alt="" class="wp-image-26164" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg 450w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">It is much more scientific to think this might be real, right?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>We can say without a shadow of a doubt that theories like this are absolutely and forever settled and that we will never find anything that contradicts them. No such evidence is even <a href="/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="post" data-id="35">possible</a>. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We completely settled such science. It would be nonsensical to pretend otherwise!</h3>



<p>So yes, there is such a thing as settled science. It is foolish to pretend otherwise. And it would be intellectually dishonest and non-scientific to pretend that we have not settled this!</p>



<p>It is unscientific to question that the Earth might not be round. Or that evolution does not happen. Or that atoms do not exist. Why? Because we have seen that the Earth is round! Are we to question the evidence of our senses so that we can become a Flattard?</p>



<p>It would contradict the obvious implications of the evidence of our senses to believe atoms do not exist. Additionally, we have seen atoms! It would go against observable facts and their logical implications to question that evolution happens.</p>



<p>It would be unscientific to question that light behaves like a wave. This would go against the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of that evidence.</p>



<p>To question theories we can show are irrefutable facts based on the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of such, is unscientific.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Your belief that the irrefutable facts of reality might be wrong is completely nonsensical and unscientific. </h3>



<p>The ability to entertain alternatives to the way reality works is not indicative of science. It is closer to the mindset of the religious person that must evade reality to maintain the possibility of his delusions. The questioning of everything, even things we can prove beyond any reasonable doubt, is little better than those that deny science outright. </p>



<p>To deny the absolute certainty of that which we can show beyond any reasonable doubt, is to either partially deny the veracity of the evidence or fail to understand that science is about the study of an objective reality, not blind guesswork.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-settled-science-scientific/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
