<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Islam &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/islam/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Rational Nonfiction Author</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 14:19:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cropped-Ashna-Dwaynes-Wedding-23-crop-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Islam &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Islam &#8212; the Cause of 9/11</title>
		<link>/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/</link>
					<comments>/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ash Davies and Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 01:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Islam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[9/11]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[morality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[September 11]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[war]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=25767</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Islamic terrorism is the cause of 9/11, despite the evasion of many in America and the rest of the West. In this article we explore the proper response to such barbarism: crushing and demoralizing the enemy!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today we shall see that the cause of 9/11 is Islamic idealogy.</p>





<p>Before the Western values of reason and individuality were attacked by Islam, stood the twin towers of the World Trade Center. These mighty structures were icons of New York City, and they stood tall and proud. </p>



<p>Before 9/11, the twin towers stood as a symbol of the heights achievable by the efforts of reasoning individuals, who value productivity, self-esteem (ego), and rationality. They were a symbol of what is achievable by individuals in a culture that values freedoms and individual rights.</p>



<p>Much like the Statue of Liberty, they were symbols of Western values. A symbol of the American Dream rooted in every individual&#8217;s right to:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-life-liberty-and-the-pursuit-of-happiness">&#8220;Life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness&#8221;</p>
<cite>DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE</cite></blockquote>



<p>The American dream is that:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-life-should-be-better-and-richer-and-fuller-for-everyone-with-opportunity-for-each-according-to-ability-or-achievement"> Life should be better and richer and fuller for everyone, with opportunity for each according to ability or achievement. </p>
<cite>James Adams, 1931.</cite></blockquote>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-february-26-1993-islam-attacks">February 26, 1993 &#8211; Islam Attacks</h2>



<p>One of the first terrorist attack on these values came on February 26, 1993. An Islamic militant, Ramzi Yousef cowardly attacked Western values. Hus Islamic ideology killed six people and injured a further 1,042 people.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the 1998 trial, Yousef condemned the United States for its American Victory over Japan in 1945 and its economic embargo against a rights-violating Cuba. &nbsp;</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-you-keep-talking-also-about-collective-punishment-and-killing-innocent-people-to-force-governments-to-change-their-policies-you-call-this-terrorism-when-someone-would-kill-innocent-people-or-civilians-in-order-to-force-the-government-to-change-its-policies-well-when-you-were-the-first-one-who-invented-this-terrorism">You keep talking also about collective punishment and killing innocent people to force governments to change their policies; you call this terrorism when someone would kill innocent people or civilians in order to force the government to change its policies. Well, when you were the first one who invented this terrorism.</p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia.</cite></blockquote>



<p>Here, Yousef clearly drops context and pretends the military defense of a nation is equivalent to terrorism if it involves the loss of innocent lives.</p>



<p>However, nobody that understands the moral justification of warfare would say such a thing. It is a moral imperative for a moral nation to engage in warfare with enemy nations and to inflict crushing military defeat upon them. </p>



<p>This always involves the loss of innocent lives. It is not feasible to expect to win a war against an enemy state without the loss of innocent lives in enemy nations. The blame for the loss of these innocent belongs to the enemy state. It is the enemy state that made the war necessary. The enemy state made it necessary to choose between innocent lives in the enemy state, or the loss of innocent lives in the nation defending itself.</p>



<p>However, the extent to which those innocent lives exist is not as great as most people think. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-most-tyrants-gain-power-by-the-consent-of-the-people-and-thus-the-population-is-guilty-of-making-such-tyranny-possible">Most tyrants gain power by the consent of the people, and thus the population is guilty of making such tyranny possible. </h3>



<p>It is immoral to equate warfare against an enemy state, a war of self-defense, with terrorism. To defend your nation against destruction by an enemy state can in no sense be equivalent to terrorism.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-you-were-the-first-one-who-killed-innocent-people-and-you-are-the-first-one-who-introduced-this-type-of-terrorism-to-the-history-of-mankind-when-you-dropped-an-atomic-bomb-which-killed-tens-of-thousands-of-women-and-children-in-japan-and-when-you-killed-over-a-hundred-thousand-people-most-of-them-civilians-in-tokyo-with-fire-bombings">You were the first one who killed innocent people, and you are the first one who introduced this type of terrorism to the history of mankind when you dropped an atomic bomb which killed tens of thousands of women and children in Japan and when you killed over a hundred thousand people, most of them civilians, in Tokyo with fire bombings. </p>



<p id="htoc-you-killed-them-by-burning-them-to-death-and-you-killed-civilians-in-vietnam-with-chemicals-as-with-the-so-called-agent-orange-you-killed-civilians-and-innocent-people-not-soldiers-innocent-people-every-single-war-you-went-you-went-to-wars-more-than-any-other-country-in-this-century-and-then-you-have-the-nerve-to-talk-about-killing-innocent-people">You killed them by burning them to death. And you killed civilians in Vietnam with chemicals, as with the so-called Agent Orange. You killed civilians and innocent people, not soldiers, innocent people every single war you went. You went to wars more than any other country in this century, and then you have the nerve to talk about killing innocent people.</p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia </cite></blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-nuclear-bombs-dropped-upon-japan-were-an-act-of-heroism">The nuclear bombs dropped upon Japan were an act of heroism. </h3>



<p>The alternative was a bloody invasion of the Japanese mainland that would have required the loss of over a million American lives, enormous expense, the destruction of much of Japan and the loss of millions of Japanese lives. </p>



<p>So it is that even the Japanese came to be thankful that the Americans found an alternative to an invasion of Japan that would have virtually destroyed Japan.</p>



<p>We must not judge the morality of a nation by the number of times it goes to war. There are legitimate reasons America may have needed to engage in war in self-defense. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img  decoding="async"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced.jpg"  alt="Ruins of Hiroshima." class="wp-image-26349" width="450" height="450" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced.jpg 600w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/600px-AtomicEffects-HiroshimaReduced-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Yes, doing this to Hiroshima was heroism. The alternative was doing this to most major Japanese cities.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>One can argue that many of the wars America has been involved in, such as the war in Vietnam or Iraq, were not justified in defending American interests but were altruistic campaigns. This is a legitimate reason to condemn America for many of its invasions.</p>



<p>But there is no legitimate reason to condemn America for Hiroshima and Nagasaki. They were a moral necessity as soon as Japan threatened America&#8217;s values of life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-and-now-you-have-invented-new-ways-to-kill-innocent-people-you-have-so-called-economic-embargo-which-kills-nobody-other-than-children-and-elderly-people-and-which-other-than-iraq-you-have-been-placing-the-economic-embargo-on-cuba-and-other-countries-for-over-35-years">And now you have invented new ways to kill innocent people. You have so-called economic embargo which kills nobody other than children and elderly people, and which other than Iraq you have been placing the economic embargo on Cuba and other countries for over 35 years. </p>



<p id="htoc-">&#8230; </p>



<p id="htoc-the-government-in-its-summations-and-opening-statement-said-that-i-was-a-terrorist-yes-i-am-a-terrorist-and-i-am-proud-of-it-and-i-support-terrorism-so-long-as-it-was-against-the-united-states-government-and-against-israel-because-you-are-more-than-terrorists-you-are-the-one-who-invented-terrorism-and-using-it-every-day-you-are-liars-butchers-and-hypocrites-29">The Government in its summations and opening statement said that I was a terrorist. Yes, I am a terrorist, and I am proud of it. And I support terrorism so long as it was against the United States Government and against Israel because you are more than terrorists; you are the one who invented terrorism and using it every day. You are liars, butchers, and hypocrites. <sup><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramzi_Yousef#cite_note-FullExcerpt-29">[29]</a></sup></p>
<cite>Ramzi Yousef, Wikipedia</cite></blockquote>



<p>Yousef condemns America for acts of violence and terrorism. He condemns America for acts of war and violence and for inventing terrorism.</p>



<p>Yet, Islam was engaging in religious terrorism long before the United States existed. It certainly did not invent terrorism, but it advocated terrorism long before America existed and long before modern Western culture existed.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-quran-contains-at-least-109-verses-describing-war-with-nonbelievers-many-are-quite-graphic-and-describe-things-such-as-the-decapitation-of-the-nonbeliever">The Quran contains at least 109 verses describing war with nonbelievers.</h3>



<p>Many of the verses are quite graphic and describe things such as the decapitation of the nonbeliever. </p>



<p>Here are some of them:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-as-to-those-who-reject-faith-i-will-punish-them-with-terrible-agony-in-this-world-and-in-the-hereafter-nor-will-they-have-anyone-to-help"><em>As to those who reject faith, I will punish them with terrible agony in this world and in the Hereafter, nor will they have anyone to help.</em></p>
<cite>Quran 3:56</cite></blockquote>



<p>Seems a clear condemnation of the so-called &#8220;crime&#8221; of non-belief.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-the-punishment-of-those-who-wage-war-against-allah-and-his-messenger-and-strive-to-make-mischief-in-the-land-is-only-this-that-they-should-be-murdered-or-crucified-or-their-hands-and-their-feet-should-be-cut-off-on-opposite-sides-or-they-should-be-imprisoned-this-shall-be-as-a-disgrace-for-them-in-this-world-and-in-the-hereafter-they-shall-have-a-grievous-chastisement"><em>The punishment of those who wage war against Allah and His messenger and strive to make mischief in the land is only this, that they should be murdered or crucified or their hands and their feet should be cut off on opposite sides or they should be imprisoned; this shall be as a disgrace for them in this world, and in the hereafter, they shall have a grievous chastisement</em></p>
<cite>Quran 5:33</cite></blockquote>



<p>And then there is this:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-remember-when-your-lord-inspired-the-angels-i-will-cast-terror-into-the-hearts-of-those-who-disbelieve-therefore-strike-off-their-heads-and-strike-off-every-fingertip-of-them"><em>&#8220;(Remember) when your Lord inspired the angels&#8230; &#8220;I will cast terror into the hearts of those who disbelieve. Therefore, strike off their heads and strike off every fingertip of them&#8221;</em></p>
<cite>Quran 8:12</cite></blockquote>



<p>The Quran predates America and modern Western culture. So, in what sense did the West invent terrorism? The Quran was clearly advocating terrorism long before America or the modern Western world was.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-the-truth-is-that-islam-is-a-death-worshiping-cult-of-widespread-genocide">The truth is that Islam is a death-worshiping cult of widespread genocide. </h3>



<p>During the trial of Yousef, Judge Duffy did not morally condemn Islam for its death worship. He apologized for Islam and faith. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img  decoding="async"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg"  alt="Picture of Muhammad." class="wp-image-26299" width="320" height="380" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg 640w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_-Prophet-_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires-253x300.jpg 253w" sizes="(max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Islam does not allow anyone to draw its deranged, murderous Prophet. But <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Everybody_Draw_Mohammed_Day_-_Depiction_of_The_%22Prophet%22_Muhammad_by_Napalm_filled_tires.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jason</a> has done just that.<br>Image available under the Creative Commons <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/deed.en" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Share-Alike License</a>.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Duffy did not condemn the sacrifice collection of such cults and religions. Duffy condemned the ego, the very Western values that had made the twin towers possible!</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-ramzi-yousef-you-claim-to-be-an-islamic-militant-of-all-the-persons-killed-or-harmed-in-some-way-by-the-world-trade-center-bomb-you-cannot-name-one-who-was-against-you-or-your-cause-you-did-not-care-just-so-long-as-you-left-dead-bodies-and-people-hurt">Ramzi Yousef, you claim to be an Islamic militant. Of all the persons killed or harmed in some way by the World Trade Center bomb, you cannot name one who was against you or your cause. You did not care, just so long as you left dead bodies and people hurt.</p>



<p id="htoc-ramzi-yousef-you-are-not-fit-to-uphold-islam-your-god-is-a-god-of-death-your-god-is-not-allah">Ramzi Yousef, you are not fit to uphold Islam. Your God is a god of death. Your God is not Allah&nbsp;&#8230;</p>



<p id="htoc-you-weren-t-seeking-conversions-the-only-thing-you-wanted-to-do-was-to-cause-death-your-god-is-not-allah-you-worship-death-and-destruction-what-you-do-you-do-not-for-allah-you-do-it-only-to-satisfy-your-twisted-sense-of-ego">You weren&#8217;t seeking conversions. The only thing you wanted to do was to cause death. Your God is not Allah. You worship death and destruction. What you do, you do not for Allah; you do it only to satisfy your twisted sense of ego.</p>



<p id="htoc-you-would-have-others-believe-that-you-are-a-soldier-but-the-attacks-on-civilization-for-which-you-stand-convicted-here-were-sneak-attacks-which-sought-to-kill-and-maim-totally-innocent-people">You would have others believe that you are a soldier, but the attacks on civilization for which you stand convicted here were sneak attacks which sought to kill and maim totally innocent people.</p>



<p id="htoc-you-ramzi-yousef-came-to-this-country-pretending-to-be-an-islamic-fundamentalist-but-you-cared-little-or-nothing-for-islam-or-the-faith-of-the-muslims-rather-you-adored-not-allah-but-the-evil-yourself-have-become-and-i-must-say-that-as-an-apostle-of-evil-you-have-been-most-effective-29">You, Ramzi Yousef, came to this country pretending to be an Islamic fundamentalist, but you cared little or nothing for Islam or the faith of the Muslims. Rather, you adored not Allah, but the evil yourself have become. And I must say that as an apostle of evil, you have been most effective. <sup><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramzi_Yousef#cite_note-FullExcerpt-29">[29]</a></sup></p>
<cite>Judge Duffy, Wikipedia</cite></blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-but-we-have-seen-that-according-to-the-quran-itself-yousef-was-acting-entirely-consistent-with-the-quran">But we have seen that according to the Quran itself, Yousef was acting entirely consistent with the Quran. </h3>



<p>The Quran has many verses like the ones given above. Not one of them says that a true Muslim shall spare heretic imprisonment or a violent death!</p>



<p>Yousef is acting just as the Quran, as Islam demands. Let us look at another quote:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-not-equal-are-those-of-the-believers-who-sit-at-home-except-those-who-are-disabled-by-injury-or-are-blind-or-lame-etc-and-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-in-the-cause-of-allah-with-their-wealth-and-their-lives-allah-has-preferred-in-grades-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-with-their-wealth-and-their-lives-above-those-who-sit-at-home-unto-each-allah-has-promised-good-paradise-but-allah-has-preferred-those-who-strive-hard-and-fight-above-those-who-sit-at-home-by-a-huge-reward"><em>Not equal are those of the believers who sit (at home), except those who are disabled (by injury or are blind or lame, etc.), and those who strive hard and fight in the Cause of Allah with their wealth and their lives. Allah has preferred in grades those who strive hard and fight with their wealth and their lives above those who sit (at home). Unto each, Allah has promised good (Paradise), but Allah has preferred those who strive hard and fight, above those who sit (at home) by a huge reward &#8220;</em></p>
<cite>Quran 4:95</cite></blockquote>



<p>This verse clearly criticizes peaceful Muslims! It holds those willing to strike the nonbeliever as morally superior to those that refuse to do so!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img  decoding="async" width="640" height="427"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion.jpg"  alt="Nuclear mushroom cloud." class="wp-image-26298" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion.jpg 640w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Atom_Bomb_Nuclear_Explosion-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">If Islamic nations, such as Iran, want wear with the US, we should give it to them&#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-september-11-2001-islam-attacks-again"><strong>September 11, 2001</strong> &#8212; Islam Attacks Again</h2>



<p>On September 11, 2001, the Western values of &#8220;life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness&#8221; were attacked again. This time, the Twin Towers collapsed. 2,192 civilians died and 414 sworn personnel died. &nbsp;</p>



<p>If only the West did not apologize for its values. If only America stood firmly and <a href="https://theobjectivestandard.com/2007/11/american-victory-over-japan-1945/?fbclid=IwAR11_faO6RxZnaEh-z5HwCehwF-XyEGnPkO1x5SLVbEvT-0c_5TFMtOz5Wk">morally behind its victory over Japan in 1945</a>. If only Judge Duffy and America had morally condemned Islamic ideologies as evil. If only&#8230;</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/never-forget-the-cause-of-9-11-is-islam/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
