<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Biology &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/biology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Rational Nonfiction Author</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 19:13:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cropped-Ashna-Dwaynes-Wedding-23-crop-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Biology &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Fragment &#038; Pandemonium Interview with Warren Fahy</title>
		<link>/fragment-pandemonium-interview/</link>
					<comments>/fragment-pandemonium-interview/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 22:35:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fragment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pandemonium]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Warren]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a republishing of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium. We are going to talk about these books as well as about some biology stuff. </p>



<p>For those unaware, the Metaphysics of Physics was the previous incarnation of this site and for a time in included a podcast.</p>



<p>You can read the transcript or use the audio player below to listen to the interview. Or do both if you prefer!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><a href="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy.mp3" data-type="URL" data-id="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy.mp3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the episode.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="introduction">Introduction</h2>



<p>Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium. We are going to talk about these books as well as about some biology stuff. Should be fun!</p>



<p>Some of you may not know what these books are. Well, Warren is going to tell us all about them in a little bit. But they are science thrillers something along the lines of Jurassic Park.</p>



<p>You can probably gather by the fact that I am interviewing him about these books, that I have read them and probably enjoy them.</p>



<p>Yes, I have read them and I do enjoy them. Fragment and the sequel are amazingly interesting books with some extremely compelling biological theories.</p>



<p>There are some truly terrifying, nightmare creatures in both of them. They make the dinosaurs and monsters in other books seem tame. Dragons? T-Rexes? The critters in these books, such as spigers are much deadlier and scarier.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img  decoding="async"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/fragement.jpg"  alt="Cover of the book Fragment." class="wp-image-26470" width="240" height="383" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/fragement.jpg 320w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/fragement-188x300.jpg 188w" sizes="(max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fragment, filled with strange creatures and fascinating biology!</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>I also quite like the main cast of characters, but I cannot talk about that very much without spoilers. But two of them are biologists and they may or may not have some fascinating biological ideas, new and old.</p>



<p>Highly recommended. But more than that and as entertaining as the scary monsters are, you might also learn something reading this.</p>



<p>If you have not read these books, you might want to go to the <a href="/fragment-pandemonium-interview-nospoiler/" data-type="post" data-id="639" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">non-spoiler version</a> of the podcast here. It has a lot of the same stuff, but with some spoiler content removed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="episode-transcript">Episode Transcript</h2>



<p>We have not presented the transcript of this in web page form. Instead, you can listen to the audio or download the PDF transcript.</p>



<p>However, there may be mistakes in the transcript. Any mistakes in transcription represent our own errors or a transcription error we missed.</p>



<p><a href="/transcripts/Episode25.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="/transcripts/Episode25.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the PDF transcript.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="brief-excerpt">Brief Excerpt</h2>



<p><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Hello, welcome to episode twenty-five of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast.<br><br>I am Dwayne Davies, your occasional host. Today we are going to interview Warren Fahy, the author of the bestselling books Fragment and Pandemonium.<br><br>Some of you may not know what these books are. Well, Warren is going to tell us all about them in a little bit. But they are science thriller something along the lines of Jurassic Park.<br><br>You can probably gather by the fact that I am interviewing him about these books, that I have read them and probably enjoy them. Yes, I have read them and I do enjoy them.<br><br>Fragment and the sequel are amazingly interesting books with some extremely compelling biological theories.</p>



<p>There are some truly terrifying, nightmare creatures in both of them. They make the dinosaurs and monsters in other books seem tame. Dragons? T-Rexes? The critters in these books, such as spigers are<br>much deadlier and scarier.<br><br>I also quite like the main cast of characters, but I cannot talk about that very much without spoilers. But two of them are biologists and they may or may not have some fascinating biological ideas, new and old.<br><br>Highly recommended. But more than that and as entertaining as the scary monsters are, you might also learn something reading this.<br><br>All right, now we have that out of the way, lets get back into things.</p>



<p>Alright, thank you for being here Warren.<br><br>Give us a brief introduction to Fragment and Pandemonium. Later questions will focus more on the science and the like, so maybe, for now, focus more on the theme and the plots.<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> Perfect. Well, Fragment and Pandemonium are science thrillers. They are somewhat in the vein of Michael Crichton books,which happened to be my favorite kind of thriller.<br><br>I like to read a thriller, get something out of it, get some new information and to learn something. So that was the kind of book I decided I wanted to write.</p>



<p>Since I was a kid, I&#8217;ve been writing. And I have been studying evolution since I dug a fossil out of the hills behind my grandparent’s home when I was eight. And ever since then I&#8217;ve been fascinated by evolution. So, I decided to mine that avenue for a thriller.<br><br>I hadn&#8217;t really seen anyone ever deal with the concept of a completely separate evolution that was isolated and went off in a completely different direction. Resulting in an entire ecosystem of almost alien creatures. If you went back far enough, I figured you could make a very compelling world.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/fragment-pandemonium-interview/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy.mp3" length="35628107" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Possible and the Impossible</title>
		<link>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/</link>
					<comments>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 02:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[impossible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=35</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we are exploring the concept of "possible" and "impossible". What does it mean for something to be possible or impossible?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today, we are exploring the concepts of the &#8220;possible&#8221; and &#8220;impossible&#8221; and their important role in cognition, particularly in the sciences.</p>





<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-possible">The Possible</h2>



<p>We must first establish the proper meaning of “possible”. I think many people, including many in science, do not grasp the meaning of this concept. Even though it is an important concept in science and all other spheres of thought.</p>



<p>Here is the definition of possible that I am using in this article:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-relating-to-a-claim-for-which-there-is-some-evidence-for-a-claim-is-possible-if-some-evidence-exists-to-support-it-being-true-and-there-is-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">Relating to a claim for which there is some evidence for. A claim is possible if some evidence exists to support it being true and there is none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it. </h3>



<p>The claim does not have to be proven true, there simply needs to be some evidence in favor of it. I consider a theory which is proven possible as it meets the above criteria. </p>



<p>In order to take any claim seriously, you should first establish that the claim is at least possible. There must be some amount of evidence that supports the claim. There must be a reason that the claim is potentially true. That the claim being made matches the fact of reality.  If you cannot do this, then your claim is arbitrary. There is no way to connect it back to reality of any kind.</p>



<p>Something is not “possible” simply because one cannot think why it is not true. One has to have a reason we should consider it to be true.</p>



<p>“X is possible” means: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-that-according-to-the-context-of-my-knowledge-there-is-some-evidence-that-x-is-true-and-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">That according to the context of my knowledge, there is some evidence that X is true and none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Note that there may not be very <em>much</em> evidence that supports X, but there must be at least some evidence.</p>



<p>The evidence might not be very conclusive, and the truth of X may still need to be verified. Tt least I have established the <em>possibility</em> of the claim. At least I have established some reason to believe that the claim might be valid.</p>



<p>Let’s take an example.</p>



<p>I wonder if humans might have evolved via a process of natural selection from some other species. I have not yet established that this is possible. It is just speculation. That I have guessed that this might be the case is not the same as establishing that it is possible. A guess in the absence of evidence does not establish that something is possible.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img  decoding="async" width="416" height="480"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg"  alt="Chimpanzee." class="wp-image-26305" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg 416w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy-260x300.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hey, seems plausible to me, this chimp looks like many people I know &#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>So, I then try to find evidence that would suggest such a thing. What kind of evidence might show this? I could look for evidence that ancient apes had primitive versions of some features humans have and that over time, later species of apes developed versions of these features that are ever closer to the version of those features shared by humans.</p>



<p>For instance, I could look at the skull of some very ancient apes. I might notice that these skulls have brain cases larger than some of their earlier relatives. These brain cases are larger than some other human relatives. However, their brain cases are not as large as the brain cases possessed by human skulls. I may then notice that later species of apes have still larger brain cases. And later generations have still larger brain cases than that. </p>



<p>And so on, so that the closer these species get to humans in time, the larger the brain cases possessed by these apes and the more human like their brain cases are. </p>



<p>What would this show? It suggests that as time progresses, that the successive species of apes are becoming more and more like humans in terms of their brain cases. We can say the same about other skeletal structures and parts of their genome! We can show that over time, we see apes that are developing increasingly human-like pelvises, for instance.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="256" height="258"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"  alt="Skull of an ancient pre-human ape." class="wp-image-26308" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg 256w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">There is much evidence that man evolved from other apes. Evidence such as this Australopithecus skull.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Therefore, it seems possible that man evolved from an ape! I have not simply asserted that it is so because I imagine it is so. I have concluded that it might be so, based on some evidence that seems to suggest this.</p>



<p>Am I certain of this? No, I might not be. I might think that this is not very conclusive yet. However, I have some reason, based on evidence, to think that it might be true. I have a <em>basis</em> for my belief that man evolved from these earlier species of apes.</p>



<p>Of course, in the modern age, we have now proven beyond all rational doubt humans did indeed evolve from other apes and that humans are still apes! We have so much evidence for this that it would be perverse to suggest that we did not evolve from apes. Sadly, this does not stop millions of Creationists from asserting that we did not evolve from apes. </p>



<p>However, suppose that I simply declare that man evolved from apes. Suppose that I have no evidence of any kind to suggest that this is true. I just assert that it is so because I simply believe it to be so, based on faith.</p>



<p>This is speculation. It is not the same as establishing that something is possible. You have no reason, no evidence, to believe it might be true. One cannot base an argument solely on speculation. Then you have simply asserted it on faith.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/the-possible-and-the-impossible/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fragment &#038; Pandemonium Interview with Warren Fahy (No Spoilers)</title>
		<link>/fragment-pandemonium-interview-nospoiler/</link>
					<comments>/fragment-pandemonium-interview-nospoiler/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 22:35:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fragment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pandemonium]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Warren]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=639</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a republishing of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium. We are going to talk about these books as well as about some biology stuff. This is the version that is hopefully free of spoilers. If you do not care about spoilers, use <a href="http://localhost/rational/fragment-pandemonium-interview/" data-type="post" data-id="641">this other version</a>. If you do, you might want to read the books first!</p>



<p>For those unaware, the Metaphysics of Physics was the previous incarnation of this site and for a time in included a podcast.</p>



<p>You can read the transcript or use the audio player below to listen to the interview. Or do both if you prefer!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy-spoiler_free.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><a href="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy-spoiler_free.mp3" data-type="URL" data-id="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy-spoiler_free.mp3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the episode.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-introduction">Introduction</h2>



<p>Today we have an interview with Warren Fahy, author of the books Fragment and Pandemonium. We are going to talk about these books as well as about some biology stuff. Should be fun!</p>



<p>Some of you may not know what these books are. Well, Warren is going to tell us all about them in a little bit. But they are science thrillers something along the lines of Jurassic Park.</p>



<p>You can probably gather by the fact that I am interviewing him about these books, that I have read them and probably enjoy them.</p>



<p>Yes, I have read them and I do enjoy them. Fragment and the sequel are amazingly interesting books with some extremely compelling biological theories.</p>



<p>There are some truly terrifying, nightmare creatures in both of them. They make the dinosaurs and monsters in other books seem tame. Dragons? T-Rexes? The critters in these books, such as spigers are much deadlier and scarier.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/rational/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/fragmentCover.jpg" alt="Fragment" class="wp-image-14998" width="230" height="387"/></figure></div>


<p>I also quite like the main cast of characters, but I cannot talk about that very much without spoilers. But two of them are biologists and they may or may not have some fascinating biological ideas, new and old.</p>



<p>Highly recommended. But more than that and as entertaining as the scary monsters are, you might also learn something reading this.</p>



<p>This is the non-spoiler version of this episode. If you have read these books, you might want to go to the other version of the<a href="http://localhost/rational/fragment-pandemonium-interview/" data-type="post" data-id="641"> podcast here</a>. It has a lot of the same stuff, but without spoiler content removed.</p>



<p>Please note that we cannot be 100% sure that there is not some spoiler we missed in here. It might be best to read the books before listening to this podcast!</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="episode-transcript">Episode Transcript</h2>



<p>We have not presented the transcript of this in web page form. Instead, you can listen to the audio or download the PDF transcript.</p>



<p>However, there may be mistakes in the transcript. Any mistakes in transcription represent our own errors or a transcription error we missed.</p>



<p><a href="/transcripts/episode25NoSpoiler.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="/transcripts/episode25NoSpoiler.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the PDF transcript.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="brief-excerpt">Brief Excerpt</h2>



<p><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Hello, welcome to episode twenty-five of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast.<br><br>I am Dwayne Davies, your occasional host. Today we are going to interview Warren Fahy, the author of the bestselling books Fragment and Pandemonium.<br><br>Some of you may not know what these books are. Well, Warren is going to tell us all about them in a little bit. But they are science thrillers something along the lines of Jurassic Park.<br><br>You can probably gather by the fact that I am interviewing him about these books, that I have read them and probably enjoy them. Yes, I have read them and I do enjoy them.<br><br>Fragment and the sequel are amazingly interesting books with some extremely compelling biological theories.<br><br>There are some truly terrifying, nightmare creatures in both of them. They make the dinosaurs and monsters in other books seem tame. Dragons? T-Rexes? The critters in these books, such as spigers are<br>much deadlier and scarier.<br><br>I also quite like the main cast of characters, but I cannot talk about that very much without spoilers. But two of them are biologists and they may or may not have some fascinating biological ideas, new and old.<br><br>Highly recommended. But more than that and as entertaining as the scary monsters are, you might also learn something reading this.<br><br>All right, now we have that out of the way, let’s get back into things.<br><br>Alright, thank you for being here Warren.<br><br>Give us a brief introduction to Fragment and Pandemonium. Later questions will focus more on the science and the like, so maybe, for now, focus more on the theme and the plots.<br><br><strong>Warren:</strong> Perfect. Well, Fragment and Pandemonium are science thrillers. They are somewhat in the vein of Michael Crichton books, which happened to be my favorite kind of thriller.<br><br>I like to read a thriller, get something out of it, get some new information and to learn something. So that was the kind of book I decided I wanted to write.Since I was a kid, I&#8217;ve been writing. </p>



<p>And I have been studying evolution ever since I dug a fossil out of the hills behind my grandparent’s home when I was eight. Ever since then I&#8217;ve been fascinated by evolution. And so, I decided to mine that avenue for a thriller.<br><br>I hadn&#8217;t really seen anyone ever deal with the concept of a completely separate evolution that was isolated and went off in a completely different direction. Resulting in an entire ecosystem of almost alien creatures. If you went back far enough, I figured you could make a very compelling world.<br><br>And so, Fragment is a story of a fragment of an ancient super-continent that had been isolated for 550 million years. And which was lost in the middle of the South Pacific Ocean in the middle of the Roaring Forties. Which is a current that ships try to avoid in their shipping routes.<br><br>I decided to put a reality TV show that is circumnavigating the world, in the path of this island. And what they discover, of course, is an alien world. Such a dangerous world that they&#8217;re almost all slaughtered on live television as they land.<br><br>And this calls attention to the United States government. The Navy isolates the island and sends in a team of scientists to find out what in the world is going on.<br><br>And what they discover is a world that if any of the species from it were to escape, and get to the rest of the world, it would be only a matter of time before they knocked out the legs from every single ecosystem on planet Earth. And so, that&#8217;s the premise of Fragment.<br><br>Pandemonium is the sequel. It has some of the survivors moving on to yet another ecosystem that has been isolated in a giant cave system under the Ural Mountains in a fictitious country.<br><br>And within that cave system, the former Soviet Union has built a gigantic city from which to escape any possible pandemonium from any kind of worldwide nuclear conflagration.<br><br>And so, then we discover an entirely different universe of creatures. We discover an ecosystem that descended not Cambrian era like Fragment but descended from the Devonian.<br><br>One in which the ecosystem is chiefly mostly molluscs instead of arthropods, like the Cambrian era descendants. And so, we once again we have another entire menu of crazy monster animals to deal with.So those are the two science-heavy books and they incorporate a lot of different new theories and required a lot of interesting research.<br><br>Dwayne: Well, that fossil you dug up when you were eight, did you ever find out what it was?<br><br>Warren: I did, it was just one leaf from a fern. </p>



<p>And my uncle was a geophysicist. And he identified it for me. He had collected a lot of trilobites from a nearby quarry and that had those really fired my imagination.<br><br>So, many years later, I would write Fragment about a world that had descended from that era, the era of trilobites. But what if they had gone off on their own way separate from everything else on planet Earth? What would they look like half a billion years later?<br><br>Dwayne: Hmm, OK. Now we can talk about some of the science ideas in the book. Tell us about some of those.<br><br>Warren: Well, since I&#8217;ve been studying evolution since I was a kid, I have been sort of a like an armchair biologist. I have always been endlessly fascinated by the process of evolution.<br><br>And three theories along the way occurred to me while I was studying various aspects of evolution. Two such theories are presented in Fragment and they are original theories.<br><br>One of them has gotten some interest from some actual geneticists who are studying lifespan. And that particular theory the theory of lifespan describes what dictates the lifespan of all species on Earth.<br><br>It was, basically, derived from looking at barnacles. And barnacles are something that fascinated Darwin to no end. They are amazing creatures which people don&#8217;t seem to really understand.<br><br>They are crustaceans like crabs or lobsters. And they&#8217;re obviously the weirdest crustacean on earth. And they only live for about two years. But mussels, that live right next to them, have almost an unlimited lifespan. They can live up to 70 years.<br><br>So, I was thinking, why in the world, would these two species have such a vastly different lifespan? And as I studied it, I realized that there was a difference between the way they procreate.Of course, mussels procreate by this huge bloom of sex cells that they all release all at the same time. Trillions of cells that drift in a cloud and end up creating the next generation.<br><br>Barnacles, however, have the largest sexual member in proportion to body size of any animal on earth. They must procreate by literally reaching it over to the next neighbor next to it in order to inseminate<br>that neighbor. That is how they create the next generation.<br><br>So that was a clue and the fact that they reach sexual maturity in one year and die. The fact that they die by the time their offspring reach sexual maturity was a giant clue.<br><br>Of course, all species on Earth become unable to procreate if they mate with their offspring. And there are all kinds of different reasons and biological barriers that stop that from happening.<br><br>And if they didn&#8217;t stop that from happening, then that species would die out in very short order. Even plants that procreate with their own offspring will become unable to procreate in only two or three<br>generations.<br><br>So, as I started to check this theory out by looking at animals and plants with lifespans, I found that the theory held true with absolutely every species across the board. Any animal that could theoretically,<br>crossbreed with their own offspring had a fixed lifespan at twice the age of sexual maturity. So that they could not compete with the next generation and mate with their own offspring.<br><br>And this is true from everything from redwoods and sequoias, to whales and to any species, you can name. But certain species get around it without lifespan, because they don&#8217;t need it.<br><br>For instance, the sequoia has made the same way that mussels do. Or the coral reefs do with giant clouds of sex sells that are all released at once. And the chances of them breeding with their own offspring are so slim that they&#8217;re infinitesimal. They are vanishingly small.<br><br>If you look at something like some whales, they congregate in giant groups and they don&#8217;t meet for life or anything. They just randomly mix in and they meet several times a year and that makes it impossible for them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/fragment-pandemonium-interview-nospoiler/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2019-07-28-fragment-pandemonium-interview-with-warren-fahy-spoiler_free.mp3" length="32829672" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is &#8220;Settled Science&#8221; Scientific?</title>
		<link>/is-settled-science-scientific/</link>
					<comments>/is-settled-science-scientific/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 09:59:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hume]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knowledge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[logic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quote4s]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://metaphysicsofphysics.com/?p=20906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some people, including alleged champions of reason and science think that there is no such thing as settled science. Let's bust that unscientific nonsense.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Is there any such thing as settled science? I am going to argue that there is.</p>



<p>What do I mean by &#8220;settled&#8221; science? A scientific claim that any rational person would accept as true and established beyond any reasonable doubt. We do not expect such theories to be replaced by an alternate theory.</p>



<p>You might object that this is not very scientific! We must always keep in mind that we might be wrong. We need to be ready to adjust what we know to accommodate new information that might cast what we know today into doubt. Keep in mind that we are fallible and that we might come to invalid conclusions.</p>



<p>All knowledge, including science, is contextual. We study reality and, based on what we observe, we form logical conclusions. But we can only account for that we know about.</p>



<p>For instance, take Newtonian gravity. In the context of not knowing what happens near the speed of light, it was entirely reasonable to accept Newton&#8217;s laws of gravity as settled science. We did not know what happened at extremely high velocities, so we had no reason to doubt Newtonian gravity. Newtonian gravity is valid, within the context of things not moving close to the speed of light. </p>



<p>We then expanded our context to account for things near light speed. We realized that in that context, Einstein’s relativity provides better mathematics for what happens with gravity at near light speed. Does that mean that we had no reason to be certain about Newtonian gravity? </p>



<p>No, it does not. We knew it was an accurate description of gravity at speeds much lower than the speed of light.</p>



<p>That is why NASA uses Newtonian gravity for most purposes, even though relativistic equations would be more accurate. Newtonian gravity is easier to deal with and is extremely accurate at the speeds NASA works with.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="500" height="559"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg"  alt="Space shuttle launch." class="wp-image-26162" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg 500w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch-268x300.jpg 268w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">You may have noticed rockets do not go at anything near the speed of light. So, Newton&#8217;s gravity equations will work just fine thanks.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Certainty is contextual. Suppose, in the context of our knowledge, the available evidence supports a theory. We should be certain about that theory. But what we are wrong? After all, we used to believe some strange things.</p>



<p>We used to think things burned because of phlogiston. Phlogiston was a mysterious substance that was thought to exist in all combustible bodies.</p>



<p>We used to think that dinosaurs were all sluggish, scaly critters that probably lived in swamps to support their massive weight.</p>



<p>Yes, sometimes we are wrong. Sometimes the facts do not support our theories. There are some theories that we have no business accepting as anything more than a plausible hypothesis.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">These are the theories that do not make up the body of settled science. These are the theories we should not consider settled. </h3>



<p>It would be dishonest to consider a theory settled in the absence of evidence. It would also be dishonest to consider a theory settled if we did not understand it well enough to be sure it was consistent with all the available evidence.</p>



<p>Some theories are entirely reasonable within the context of the available evidence. Sometimes all the known evidence points to these theories being true. </p>



<p>Sometimes we understand the theory well enough to conclude it is entirely consistent with the facts. If the facts are consistent with that theory and only that theory, then we can be certain that the theory in question is true.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We should not entertain serious doubts about theories that have substantial evidence behind them. </h3>



<p>We can always <em>imagine</em> that we might disprove some theories. However, we should be certain about a theory if all the available evidence points to it being true.</p>



<p>Certainty does not require us to account for, by magic, for the possibility of a context of knowledge we do not currently possess. We can be certain that something is true even if there is something we do not know about now that may later show that it is not true.</p>



<p>Certainty is contextual, it is valid to be certain based on the context of available evidence. Provided that we are willing to address any evidence that arises, should the context of our knowledge change. We can be certain something is true. And yet adjust our theories when the context of our knowledge expands.</p>



<p>However, there are theories that we can consider completely and forever settled. These are theories we know with certainty and can prove with no shadow of a doubt to be true.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We know these facts are true and that we cannot show them to be false.</h3>



<p>It would contradict known facts of reality if they were not true. Things would have to not be what we know they are.</p>



<p>Examples of these would be that atoms exist. We know atoms exist; we have seen them. If they did not exist, almost everything we know about chemistry and atomic physics would not be true.</p>



<p>We know evolution happens. We might not know everything about how it happens, but we know it does. If I wanted disprove evolution, we would have to invalidate almost everything we know about biology and the known facts of biology would have to be other than what they are.</p>



<p>We know the Earth is round and that it orbits the Sun. To invalidate this, the direct evidence of our senses would have to be wrong! That we can see that the Earth is round would have to be fake. And how would we explain the observed behavior of Earth if it does not orbit the Sun? </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg"><img  decoding="async" width="450" height="450"  src="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg"  alt="" class="wp-image-26164" srcset="https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg 450w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d3r1y5pfd801i1.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">It is much more scientific to think this might be real, right?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>We can say without a shadow of a doubt that theories like this are absolutely and forever settled and that we will never find anything that contradicts them. No such evidence is even <a href="/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="post" data-id="35">possible</a>. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">We completely settled such science. It would be nonsensical to pretend otherwise!</h3>



<p>So yes, there is such a thing as settled science. It is foolish to pretend otherwise. And it would be intellectually dishonest and non-scientific to pretend that we have not settled this!</p>



<p>It is unscientific to question that the Earth might not be round. Or that evolution does not happen. Or that atoms do not exist. Why? Because we have seen that the Earth is round! Are we to question the evidence of our senses so that we can become a Flattard?</p>



<p>It would contradict the obvious implications of the evidence of our senses to believe atoms do not exist. Additionally, we have seen atoms! It would go against observable facts and their logical implications to question that evolution happens.</p>



<p>It would be unscientific to question that light behaves like a wave. This would go against the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of that evidence.</p>



<p>To question theories we can show are irrefutable facts based on the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of such, is unscientific.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Your belief that the irrefutable facts of reality might be wrong is completely nonsensical and unscientific. </h3>



<p>The ability to entertain alternatives to the way reality works is not indicative of science. It is closer to the mindset of the religious person that must evade reality to maintain the possibility of his delusions. The questioning of everything, even things we can prove beyond any reasonable doubt, is little better than those that deny science outright. </p>



<p>To deny the absolute certainty of that which we can show beyond any reasonable doubt, is to either partially deny the veracity of the evidence or fail to understand that science is about the study of an objective reality, not blind guesswork.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/is-settled-science-scientific/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
