<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Epistemology &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<atom:link href="https://dwaynedavies.com/tag/epistemology/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://dwaynedavies.com</link>
	<description>Rational Nonfiction Author</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 19:08:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cropped-Ashna-Dwaynes-Wedding-23-crop-1-32x32.jpg</url>
	<title>Epistemology &#8211; Dwayne Davies</title>
	<link>https://dwaynedavies.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Absurdity of Faith</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 22:43:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bible quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=657</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this article, I am going to demonstrate that faith is by its very nature unreasonable and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="d19e">In this article, I am going to show that religious faith is unreasonable, and that no honest person should ever exercise faith. We can make very similar arguments about other kinds of faith. However, we will focus on religious faith.</p>


<h2 class="simpletoc-title">Table of Contents</h2>
<ol class="simpletoc-list">
<li><a href="#what-is-faith">What is Faith?</a></li>
<li><a href="#what-is-the-harm">What is the Harm?</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#justified-trust">Is Biblical Faith “Justified Trust”?</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#bible-quotes">Bible Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="4/#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li></ol>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-faith"><strong>What is Faith?</strong></h2>


<p id="63a2">I define faith as:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-the-blind-acceptance-of-assertions-in-the-absence-of-any-evidence-or-proof-based-on-the-emotional-desire-for-that-assertion-to-be-true"><em>The blind acceptance of assertions in the absence of any evidence or proof, based on the emotional desire for that assertion to be true.</em></p>
<cite>Dwayne Davies</cite></blockquote>



<p id="17ba">The only claims of any merit are those that help us achieve some good value or another. That value might be to understand how to deal with the world around you and stay alive. It might be how to get lots of money and buy that house you want. It could be any value that you might imagine. </p>



<p id="17ba">However, for a value and claim to be of worth, it must help us achieve some purpose based on reality. If not, of what use could it possibly be to anyone?</p>



<p>To achieve good values, we must deal with the world as it really is. We must understand how the world works and deal with reality as it is. Only the things that help us do this help us to achieve values. Therefore, in order to help us achieve values in the real world, a claim must have a valid relation to the world. It must have some relation to observable facts. If not, then it is impossible for it to have any merit. That which has no relation to the real world is useless in achieving values. </p>



<p>If we are going to make or evaluate claims about reality, the only ones that are of any use in achieving values are those that correspond with reality. Truth is correspondence with reality. Truth is that which corresponds to the way things are. Therefore, the only claim that has any merit is that which has some truth to it.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="500" height="419" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg" alt="Earth under a dome (the firmament)." class="wp-image-26326" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500.jpg 500w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/firmament500-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Bible seems to think the Earth is flat and with a over it. Possibly with stars embedded into the dome. But we should not take its word for any of that, should we?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>But how do we know whether a claim is true? You must first establish the possibility of the claim. If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. If you make an assertion without evidence, we cannot show it to correspond to reality. That assertion is, therefore, entirely without merit.</p>



<p>How do we establish whether something is possible? We discuss that in <a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this article on possibility.</a> Indeed, we took much of this section from that article.</p>



<p>To summarize that article, before we take any claim seriously, we must first establish that there is some evidence that it might be true. Otherwise, it is a waste of time considering it. </p>



<p id="2b1f">If we make a claim, we should establish that there is some evidence or proof behind it. Why should anyone accept any claim in the absence of evidence? Why would anyone do this when it could have no objective value? </p>



<p>Because they want it to be true. They have no cognitive reason to want it to be true. That person simply feels that it is preferable for it to be true. They feel an emotional response to the assertions being made, which makes them want to believe that the assertion must be true. </p>



<p>There is no reason to accept something merely because you want it to be true. Emotions are not tools of cognition. A claim is not valid because you wish it to be so. </p>



<p>But that is what faith is, the acceptance of things for which there is no evidence or proof. Faith is, therefore, the acceptance of baseless assertions for no reason and because someone wants it to be true based on emotion. However, emotions are not a valid reason for believing something.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-the-harm">What is the Harm?</h2>


<p id="fba5">Faith and reality are always in conflict. So is virtually every claim accepted for no reason and defended against reason. Knowing the truth is not a trivial task. It requires careful observation of reality, serious thought and a dedication to understanding the facts for what they are. </p>



<p id="a0eb">Faith is the refusal to do any of that. Faith is the attempt to bypass thought and proceed directly to the truth by wishing empty assertions to be fact. As though wanting something to be true somehow makes it so.</p>



<p id="622c">Assertions accepted on faith are almost always wrong. There is no real chance that anything you believe for no reason corresponds to the facts. There is essentially no chance that your blind assertions are true.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg" alt="Eve presents Adam the apple in the snake's mouth." class="wp-image-26328" width="640" height="426" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller.jpg 640w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Franz-Von-Stuck-adam-and-EveSmaller-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The story of Adam and Eve condemns man for having the knowledge of good and evil. Condemns man for seeking an understanding of the world&#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Which is why the Bible is almost invariably wrong about everything. It is wrong about the shape of the Earth, and when it asserts that pi is exactly three. It is wrong when it pretends that Earth has a glass dome above it that lets the rain in. There are lots of other silly examples like this.</p>



<p>Therefore, almost everything every religion says about the universe is wrong. That is why their cosmologies are always wrong. That is why, when religions say what is right or wrong, they are frequently wrong.</p>



<p>Many religions prohibit things like theft or murder, in certain circumstances. The Bible includes commandments not to steal or murder. Most of us would agree that these are objectively wrong. These are examples of the few instances of things in the Bible that reasonable people might agree with.</p>



<p>However, the Bible does not forbid murder because of any valid reasoning. It does not forbid killing people because of any real respect for individual rights. It does this because it asserts God would not like this for reasons that are not entirely clear.  It is the same with stealing, which is not forbidden because of any arguments to do with property rights, but again for reasons that God does not make clear.</p>



<p>So even when it forbids things that reasonable people might consider wrong, it does not do so for valid reasons. Religions forbid things for invalid reasons and manage to once again prove that they are wrong. </p>



<p id="f195">Once you have rejected reality and embraced faith, what does that leave you to believe? Whatever you want to believe in, as long as we assume it blindly.</p>



<p id="63fe">Most often, this takes the form of whatever is emotionally satisfying or seems superficially easy to grasp. Or which provides moral guidance with little to no actual connection to how man should act to be happy and thrive.</p>



<p id="0e6a">But just because something is easy to understand does not mean that it is true. Something like the theory of a flat Earth might seem intuitive. However, the Earth is not flat. </p>



<p>It seemed intuitive to the Greeks that there were no <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">irr</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">ational numbers</a>. However, they were wrong and irrational numbers turn up all the time in mathematics. </p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-absurdity-of-faith/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating Christ Interview with James Valliant</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 22:37:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Book Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christianity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Creating Christ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Valliant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Roman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romans]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=645</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we interview James Valliant, author of the important book "Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors Invented Christianity". ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a republishing of the Metaphysics of Physics podcast interview with James Valliant, one of the authors of the book Creating Christ. We talk about this important book and what it reveals about the Roman origins of Christianity. </p>



<p>For those unaware, the Metaphysics of Physics was the previous incarnation of this site and for a time in included a podcast.</p>



<p>You can read the transcript or use the audio player below to listen to the interview. Or do both if you prefer!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p><a href="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" data-type="URL" data-id="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a> to download the episode.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-introduction">Introduction</h2>


<p>Today we interview James Valliant, author of the important book &#8220;<a href="https://www.creatingchrist.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors Invented Christianity</a>&#8220;. This interview is basically a question-led interview and provides long answers to the relatively few questions which were required.</p>



<p>Please note that some of our interviews reference &#8220;Metaphysics of Physics&#8221;. This was the previous incarnation of the Rational Metaphysician.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-about-creating-christ">About Creating Christ</h2>


<p>The thesis of Creating Christ is that Christianity is the result of Roman propaganda in the first and second centuries. Designed to pacify Messianic Jews and to integrate them into Roman society.</p>



<p>This might not seem to be an important subject or a probable claim, but it really is. If Christianity and its proper place in the history of the West is to be understood, it is important that the true nature of Christianity is understood.</p>



<p>But, is this claim true? Yes, as you will discover when you listen to the podcast and or read the transcript.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist.jpg" alt="Cover of the Creating Christ book." class="wp-image-26420" width="263" height="394" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist.jpg 350w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/CreatingChrist-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /></figure></div>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-episode-transcript">Episode Transcript</h2>


<p>This episode is about one hour and fifty-six minutes long. As a result, we have not implemented the episode transcript in the usual form. We have provided a transcript in an edited and more formal form. It is much like a formal written answer to the question, however, the questions do very closely match the content of the audio.</p>



<p>However, please note that there may be minor mistakes in the transcript. I have done my best to clean up any spelling and grammatical errors, however, due to time constraints, it has not been possible to edit out all possibility of such.</p>



<p><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode_ten.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/transcripts/episode_ten.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here to download the PDF transcript.</a></p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-brief-excerpt">Brief Excerpt</h2>


<p><strong>Ashna: James, please introduce yourself and explain the thesis of the book:</strong></p>



<p><strong>James:</strong> My name is James Valliant. I am the co-author of the new book &#8220;Creating Christ: How Roman Emperors invented Christianity&#8221;.<br><br>Basically, it takes on what would certainly strike most people today, certainly most Christians today, as a rather outrageous thesis. That in fact, the New Testament is Roman propaganda. That when it was originally written, it was written with a certain political agenda. As well as a certain theological agenda.</p>



<p>Most Christians would think that is crazy. They regard Christianity as the very opposite of Roman philosophy. They believe that the Romans persecuted Christianity. Hollywood has certainly convinced them that in the last century. But, there&#8217;s a forgotten history here.</p>



<p>Two thousand years ago, there was cataclysmic war between the Roman Empire and Jewish Messianic rebels. And the rebellion was largely motivated by religious factors. It was that war, that cataclysmic war, that destroyed the temple, for example. Reduced it to the Wailing Wall that it is today.</p>



<p>It is difficult for me to imagine that Christianity emerging at that very same moment in history is just an accident. And when we started our research, we found nothing to contradict our theory. And then we found some remarkable physical evidence which basically demonstrated it.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-rounded">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="237" height="240" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda.jpg" alt="Roman coin." class="wp-image-26421" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda.jpg 237w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/coin_Roman-propaganda-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 237px) 100vw, 237px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Like many Roman coins were, Christianity is naked Roman propaganda.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In short, the thesis is that what we have in the New Testament is Roman propaganda written 2000 years ago to quell the Jewish revolt. That is very much the 30,000-foot level of analysis. Or I should say 10,000-meter level, from New Zealand. [footnote]Dwayne and Ashna were living in New Zealand when this was recorded[/footnote]</p>



<p>So, from way up in the sky, looking down on it, the way to really look at it is that the moral idealism that we read in the New Testament is really a form of political propaganda.</p>



<p>It is also regarded as moral idealism, both by Christians and even by secular people who have adopted it.</p>



<p>And having forgotten the original context of the New Testament&#8217;s creation, it&#8217;s very easy to detach ourselves from that. And to think of the doctrine of Jesus Christ as sort of an unworldly, non-earthly form of moral idealism.</p>



<p>But when you just change the angle slightly and you look at the entire New Testament from this new angle, suddenly everything is explained. We were simply blown away, I think when we started pulling that string because nothing contradicted it. And all the evidence seemed to confirm it.</p>



<p><strong>Ashna: Does it matter how Christianity got started? Why does that matter to us now?</strong></p>



<p><strong>James:</strong> Well, that&#8217;s a fair question. This is 2000-year-old history and Christianity has certainly changed considerably. At least it&#8217;s operative doctrines have. The New Testament itself obviously has not changed, but the way Christians understand and live those doctrines has dramatically changed over the last 2000 years.</p>



<p>So that&#8217;s a very good question. Why should we even care? Well, there are two very good answers to that. History matters. And particularly the history of ideas.</p>



<p>Human beings are really motivated by their ideas and their history can be understood in terms of the power of ideas. Although these ideas are 2000 years old, they literally reach across the millennia and control our psychologies, our view of what&#8217;s morally right and wrong.</p>



<p>Even people who are secular, people who tend to be on political left and who don&#8217;t have much of a religion, have basically adopted Christian social ethics is their own. Socialists and Communists have basically applied the ethics and the social doctrine of the New Testament in a very consistentway. While simply leaving out all the mystical and miraculous stuff.</p>



<p>So, the values and the ideas expressed in the New Testament are still a living vital, powerful force. On the American left, they have adopted elements of pacifism, social altruism and concern for the poor above other considerations.</p>



<p>The discovery, whether you&#8217;re religious or not, that the moral idealism of Christianity is in fact simply a form of political propaganda, is crucially important.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-creating-christ-author/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://d1b27fxioefwtw.cloudfront.net/2018-12-24-interview-with-the-author-of-creating-christ.mp3" length="73837935" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview on Induction &#038; Physics with James Ellias</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-ellias-physics-induction/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-ellias-physics-induction/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 22:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ellias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[induction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[philosophy of phsyics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy of Science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=635</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is an interview with James Ellias, creator of the excellent "An Inductive Summary of Physics" series covering the role of induction in the history of physics and more.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">This is an interview with James Ellias, creator of the excellent &#8220;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bQ53xy9gRLw&amp;list=PL7mrYYFgBAuEzwEQn5auLnSg4DzRXlyoB" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bQ53xy9gRLw&amp;list=PL7mrYYFgBAuEzwEQn5auLnSg4DzRXlyoB" target="_blank">An Inductive Summary of Physics</a>&#8221; series covering the role of induction in the history of physics and other important philosophical topics.</p>



<p class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">We discuss the role of induction in physics and many other issues in the philosophy of physics. As well as taking a few questions from our listeners.<br><br>If you are interested in induction, check out our interview on <a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/induction-in-computer-science-livestream/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://dwaynedavies.com/induction-in-computer-science-livestream/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">induction and computer science here</a>.</p>



<p>You should also read the book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Logical-Leap-Induction-Physics/dp/0451230051" target="_blank" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.amazon.com/Logical-Leap-Induction-Physics/dp/0451230051" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Logical Leap</a> by Leonard Peikoff and David Harriman.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/The-Logical-Leap.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-26474" width="309" height="464" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/The-Logical-Leap.jpg 412w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/The-Logical-Leap-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 309px) 100vw, 309px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Logical Leap: Induction in Physics</figcaption></figure></div>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-questions-asked">Questions Asked</h2>


<p class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">The questions asked in the interview include (please note that the questions are not necessarily listed in the order asked):</p>



<ul type="video" class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">
<li>Tell us more about the role of induction in physics.<br></li>



<li>What would you add to or change about the theory of induction presented in the Logical Leap? Or what do you have to say about induction in general?<br></li>



<li>Tell us about your video “There are two hierarchies of knowledge”.<br></li>



<li>Alright, tell us about the role of mathematics in physics<br></li>



<li>Tell us about the “Brief History of Physics” series on your YouTube channel.<br></li>



<li>So, tell us the “Inductive Summary of Physics” project.<br></li>



<li>Who are some of your favorite physicists?&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of your favorite sources of inspiration for your work? Which authors/speakers do you draw the most from/get the most inspiration from?<br></li>



<li>Would you care to tell us any of your ideas about what really be going on with some of the lesser well known parts of modern physics? I am talking about things like quantum mechanics, what fields really are, what relativity is really describing and so on.<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of your experiences in academia? Is going into academia something you would recommend for those interested in physics? Why or why not?<br></li>



<li>What do you think is wrong with modern physics? What are some of the root causes?<br></li>



<li>Which books/sources would you recommend to learn more about physics?<br></li>



<li>In what ways is philosophy important to physics?&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>Why do you think so many physicists dismiss philosophy?<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of the most ingenious experiments performed in physics.<br></li>



<li>Talk about the difference between the historical approach and your inductive approach.&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>What do you think about Lewis Littles’ Theory of Elementary Waves?</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">To find out the answers to these questions, you should tune into the interview&#8230; <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Livestream with James Ellias" width="900" height="506" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQbapEEMHDo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p class="wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">You can find his <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC6ERVovZaB0eT0xkwKHESlA" target="_blank">YouTube channel here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-ellias-physics-induction/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Possible and the Impossible</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 02:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Launch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Religion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evolution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[impossible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Possible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=35</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today we are exploring the concept of "possible" and "impossible". What does it mean for something to be possible or impossible?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today, we are exploring the concepts of the &#8220;possible&#8221; and &#8220;impossible&#8221; and their important role in cognition, particularly in the sciences.</p>


<h2 class="simpletoc-title">Table of Contents</h2>
<ol class="simpletoc-list" style="padding-left:0;list-style:none;">
<li><a href="#the-possible">The Possible</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="#htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it.</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#htoc-just-because-a-claim-is-true-does-not-mean-it-is-possible-in-the-absence-of-evidence">Just because a claim is true does not mean you have established that it is  true or possible in the absence of evidence.</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><a href="2/#what-counts-as-evidence">What Counts as Evidence?</a></li>
<li><a href="2/#the-impossible">The Impossible</a>
<ol><li>
<a href="2/#htoc-if-you-can-establish-if-x-was-true-it-would-contradict-a-known-fact-then-x-cannot-be-possible">If you can establish that if X was true, it would contradict a known fact, then X cannot be possible.</a></li>
<li><a href="3/#htoc-that-which-contradicts-with-any-known-fact-of-reality-is-impossible">That which contradicts any known fact of reality is impossible.</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><a href="3/#why-does-this-matter">Why Does this Matter?</a></li></ol>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-possible">The Possible</h2>


<p>We must first establish the proper meaning of “possible”. I think many people, including many in science, do not grasp the meaning of this concept. Even though it is an important concept in science and all other spheres of thought.</p>



<p>Here is the definition of possible that I am using in this article:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-relating-to-a-claim-for-which-there-is-some-evidence-for-a-claim-is-possible-if-some-evidence-exists-to-support-it-being-true-and-there-is-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">Relating to a claim for which there is some evidence for. A claim is possible if some evidence exists to support it being true and there is none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="htoc-a-claim-is-possible-if-you-can-find-some-evidence-to-support-it">A claim is possible if you can find some evidence to support it. </h3>


<p>The claim does not have to be proven true, there simply needs to be some evidence in favor of it. I consider a theory which is proven possible as it meets the above criteria. </p>



<p>In order to take any claim seriously, you should first establish that the claim is at least possible. There must be some amount of evidence that supports the claim. There must be a reason that the claim is potentially true. That the claim being made matches the fact of reality.  If you cannot do this, then your claim is arbitrary. There is no way to connect it back to reality of any kind.</p>



<p>Something is not “possible” simply because one cannot think why it is not true. One has to have a reason we should consider it to be true.</p>



<p>“X is possible” means: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p id="htoc-that-according-to-the-context-of-my-knowledge-there-is-some-evidence-that-x-is-true-and-none-that-proves-that-it-is-not-true">That according to the context of my knowledge, there is some evidence that X is true and none that proves that it is not true.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Note that there may not be very <em>much</em> evidence that supports X, but there must be at least some evidence.</p>



<p>The evidence might not be very conclusive, and the truth of X may still need to be verified. Tt least I have established the <em>possibility</em> of the claim. At least I have established some reason to believe that the claim might be valid.</p>



<p>Let’s take an example.</p>



<p>I wonder if humans might have evolved via a process of natural selection from some other species. I have not yet established that this is possible. It is just speculation. That I have guessed that this might be the case is not the same as establishing that it is possible. A guess in the absence of evidence does not establish that something is possible.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="416" height="480" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg" alt="Chimpanzee." class="wp-image-26305" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy.jpg 416w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/chimpGuy-260x300.jpg 260w" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Hey, seems plausible to me, this chimp looks like many people I know &#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>So, I then try to find evidence that would suggest such a thing. What kind of evidence might show this? I could look for evidence that ancient apes had primitive versions of some features humans have and that over time, later species of apes developed versions of these features that are ever closer to the version of those features shared by humans.</p>



<p>For instance, I could look at the skull of some very ancient apes. I might notice that these skulls have brain cases larger than some of their earlier relatives. These brain cases are larger than some other human relatives. However, their brain cases are not as large as the brain cases possessed by human skulls. I may then notice that later species of apes have still larger brain cases. And later generations have still larger brain cases than that. </p>



<p>And so on, so that the closer these species get to humans in time, the larger the brain cases possessed by these apes and the more human like their brain cases are. </p>



<p>What would this show? It suggests that as time progresses, that the successive species of apes are becoming more and more like humans in terms of their brain cases. We can say the same about other skeletal structures and parts of their genome! We can show that over time, we see apes that are developing increasingly human-like pelvises, for instance.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="256" height="258" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg" alt="Skull of an ancient pre-human ape." class="wp-image-26308" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull.jpg 256w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-150x150.jpg 150w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/lucySkull-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">There is much evidence that man evolved from other apes. Evidence such as this Australopithecus skull.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Therefore, it seems possible that man evolved from an ape! I have not simply asserted that it is so because I imagine it is so. I have concluded that it might be so, based on some evidence that seems to suggest this.</p>



<p>Am I certain of this? No, I might not be. I might think that this is not very conclusive yet. However, I have some reason, based on evidence, to think that it might be true. I have a <em>basis</em> for my belief that man evolved from these earlier species of apes.</p>



<p>Of course, in the modern age, we have now proven beyond all rational doubt humans did indeed evolve from other apes and that humans are still apes! We have so much evidence for this that it would be perverse to suggest that we did not evolve from apes. Sadly, this does not stop millions of Creationists from asserting that we did not evolve from apes. </p>



<p>However, suppose that I simply declare that man evolved from apes. Suppose that I have no evidence of any kind to suggest that this is true. I just assert that it is so because I simply believe it to be so, based on faith.</p>



<p>This is speculation. It is not the same as establishing that something is possible. You have no reason, no evidence, to believe it might be true. One cannot base an argument solely on speculation. Then you have simply asserted it on faith.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview with Narendra Kumar on Science Education</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-on-science-education/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-on-science-education/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 01:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[learnig]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy of Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost/rational/?p=82</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is the transcript of an interview with my friend Narendra Kumar. We discussed the difficulties of learning science, problems with concretization, the role of mathematics and more.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is the transcript of an interview with my friend Narendra Kumar on the issue of science education. We discussed many things, including the difficulties of learning physics, problems with concretization, the role of mathematics and its relationship with science, the beauty of the science and more.</p>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="introduction">Introduction</h2>


<p>I answered some of the questions he prepared in advance and he offered several insightful clarifying questions and commentary. It was a very good interview and we covered a lot of ground in about seventy minute.</p>



<p>This was supposed to be a livestream available on YouTube. However there were severe audio issues and much of the audio is unusable. However, I have created this transcript without losing anything significant from the original discussion.</p>



<p>At a later date I will present an audio reading of this interview which is mostly my answers but with several of Narendra&#8217;s insightful comments. For now, you have this transcript.</p>



<p>I trust that you will find this interesting and informative. The transcript is available below as a PDF, please <a href="http://localhost/rational/transcripts/MetaphysicsOfPhysicsInterviewWithNarendra.pdf" data-type="URL" data-id="http://localhost/rational/transcripts/MetaphysicsOfPhysicsInterviewWithNarendra.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">click here download it</a>.</p>



<p>Please note that some of our interviews reference &#8220;Metaphysics of Physics&#8221;. This was the previous incarnation of the Rational Metaphysician.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="600" height="480" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Eratosthenes.jpg" alt="Eratosthenes teaching." class="wp-image-26412" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Eratosthenes.jpg 600w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Eratosthenes-300x240.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eratosthenes" target="_blank" data-type="URL" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eratosthenes" rel="noreferrer noopener">Eratosthenes</a>, he did some good early science.</figcaption></figure></div>

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="excerpt-of-the-interview-on-science-education">Excerpt of the Interview on Science Education</h2>


<p><strong>Dwayne</strong>: Okay. Hi everyone, and welcome to another episode of the Metaphysics of Physics.<br><strong><br>Narendra:</strong> Hi.<br><br>Today I have my friend Narendra with us from India, via the magic of the internet. Say hi to our audience.<br><br><strong>Narendra:</strong> Hello everybody!<br><strong><br>Dwayne:</strong> He teaches English studies. And he likes to use holistic education methods. And he has a Bachelor’s degree in Civil Engineering and an MSc in Economics.<br><br>We are going to learn about some issues in science and science education. We&#8217;ll be focusing on physics, but a lot of other branches of science, particularly mathematics, will come up as well. Narendra has given me lots of good questions beforehand.<br><strong><br>Narendra:</strong> Yeah, they&#8217;ve already given. And so, thank you, Dwayne, I would like to say something.<br><br>I am happy that I&#8217;ve come on live with you. I&#8217;ve been watching your posts and the way you over-explain. I really love that. So, I thought we&#8217;ll connect, and thanks for agreeing to that.<br><br>And thanks also for the fantastic preparation you have done. Because I gave these questions much earlier, almost, I think two weeks back. And he wrote the answers down. So that&#8217;s very unique. People don&#8217;t do that.<br><br><strong>Dwayne: </strong>Well, I like to be prepared.<br><br><strong>Narendra: </strong>Yeah, I know, I know. I&#8217;d like to tell the audience that these questions have already been given. So, there&#8217;s no need for me to ask them. He will be telling the question.<br><br>And I will be adding things. If I think that there is anything if I feel a general audience needs it. If they need some clarification or if I need some clarification, I&#8217;ll butt in. But I would like Dwayne to talk.Dwayne: Yes.<br><br><strong>Narendra:</strong> Okay, then we go ahead.<br><br><strong>Dwayne: </strong>Okay, let&#8217;s get started with the first question. And this question is whether it is difficult to learn physics. And here&#8217;s what I have to say on that.<br><br>Now, of course, physics is a very fundamental subject. Some people might have the idea that this should make it easy, but I do not think that should be the case. Fundamental is not the same as easy.<br><br>The subject matter of physics is essentially all of physical reality. You can take the view that that is looking out at all of physical reality and seeing how all of this works. Basically, everything that is physical is something to do with physics.<br><br>But in practice, this is not actually easy. Once you start doing physics, you will very quickly find that you need math, lots of math, to do much of anything.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" width="450" height="338" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/hard-math.jpg" alt="Complicated math." class="wp-image-26413" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/hard-math.jpg 450w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/hard-math-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">This is not where physics stops. It where it should really get going &#8230;</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Narendra:</strong> Yes.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> You need to be able to quantify the things like velocity, and acceleration and forces and how forces lead to motion and stuff. You need mathematics to identify, quantify, understand all these relationships. We will go into the role of math in a later question, and so we won&#8217;t go into that too<br>much now.<br><br><strong>Narendra: </strong>Yeah.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> But the math can get really complicated, really fast. And not everyone is good at math. Certainly not in my experience. It is a very abstract subject, and it&#8217;s very difficult for some, even if it is taught properly. And in my experience, it seldom is.<br><br>Add to that the fact that you&#8217;re dealing with some very abstract things like energy. We don&#8217;t know what energy is really and Feynman himself said we don&#8217;t know. And he was one of the greatest physicists of his time.<br><br><strong>Narendra:</strong> He did not know; you can imagine it was undefined.</p>



<p><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Yeah, that was a perfectly valid point. So, in other words, energy is not easy to intuitively grasp. And then there&#8217;s light. We don&#8217;t know what light really is. They say it&#8217;s a particle and a wave. But, well, no.<br><br>Even trying to visualize an atom can be hard. Remember the show the Big Bang Theory? You have that picture of the electrons orbiting the nucleus like little moons.<br><br>This is an okay way of visualizing an atom. It is good enough for high school physics, maybe first-year college physics. But according to quantum physics, this is wrong. But how do we visualize it?<br><strong><br>Narendra:</strong> Exactly.<br><br><strong>Dwayne: </strong>We don&#8217;t know, quantum physics has not given us an answer. It doesn&#8217;t give us any answers.</p>



<p>So, you could say that the subject matter of physics is non-trivial to understand. It can get quite abstract. But there is another problem.<br><br>Many of the problems of modern physics make this a lot harder than it should be. You see, there is a &#8220;shut up and calculate&#8221; approach that is widely taken.<br><br><strong>Narendra: </strong>Shut and calculate.<br><br><strong>Dwayne:</strong> Yeah.<br><br><strong>Narendra: </strong>Shut up and calculate. Yeah, that is funny. Shut up and calculate.<br><br>Dwayne: Yes, exactly. That is an exact quote, although I cannot remember who said it offhand.<br><br><strong>Narendra: </strong>Oh, my.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-on-science-education/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interview with James Ellias</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-james-ellias/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-james-ellias/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 10:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Interviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interview]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quantum physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[relativity]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://metaphysicsofphysics.com/?p=21407</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is an interview with James Ellias, creator of the excellent "An Inductive Summary of Physics" series covering an inductive history of physics and other important philosophical topics.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is an interview with James Ellias, creator of the excellent &#8220;<a href="https://metaphysicsofphysics.com/the-inductive-summary-of-physics-project/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">An Inductive Summary of Physics</a>&#8221; series covering an inductive history of physics and other important philosophical topics.</p>



<p>We discuss the role of induction in physics and many other issues in the philosophy of physics. As well as taking a few questions from our listeners.</p>



<p>The questions asked in the interview include (please not the questions are not necceasirly listed in the order asked):</p>



<ul class="blog-list">
<li>Tell us more about the role of induction in physics.<br></li>



<li>What would you add to or change about the theory of induction presented in the Logical Leap? Or what do you have to say about induction in general?<br></li>



<li>Tell us about your video “There are two hierarchies of knowledge”.<br></li>



<li>Alright, tell us about the role of mathematics in physics<br></li>



<li>Tell us about the “Brief History of Physics” series on your YouTube channel.<br></li>



<li>So, tell us the “Inductive Summary of Physics” project.<br></li>



<li>Who are some of your favorite physicists?&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of your favorite sources of inspiration for your work? Which authors/speakers do you draw the most from/get the most inspiration from?<br></li>



<li>Would you care to tell us any of your ideas about what really be going on with some of the lesser well known parts of modern physics? I am talking about things like quantum mechanics, what fields really are, what relativity is really describing and so on.<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of your experiences in academia? Is going into academia something you would recommend for those interested in physics? Why or why not?<br></li>



<li>What do you think is wrong with modern physics? What are some of the root causes?<br></li>



<li>Which books/sources would you recommend to learn more about physics?<br></li>



<li>In what ways is philosophy important to physics?&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>Why do you think so many physicists dismiss philosophy?<br></li>



<li>Tell us about some of the most ingenious experiments performed in physics.<br></li>



<li>Talk about the difference between the historical approach and your inductive approach.&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>What do you think about Lewis Littles’ Theory of Elementary Waves?</li>
</ul>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/bohr-and-einstein.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/bohr-and-einstein.jpg" alt="Bohr and Einstein arguing." class="wp-image-26384" width="379" height="393" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/bohr-and-einstein.jpg 505w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/bohr-and-einstein-289x300.jpg 289w" sizes="(max-width: 379px) 100vw, 379px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bohr and Einstein, two of the founders of modern physics.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>To find out the answers to these questions, you should tune into the interview&#8230; <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f642.png" alt="🙂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Livestream with James Ellias" width="900" height="506" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oQbapEEMHDo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>You can find his <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC6ERVovZaB0eT0xkwKHESlA" target="_blank">YouTube channel here</a>.</p>



<p>You can find his <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQbapEEMHDo&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">Inductive Summary of Physics channel here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/interview-with-james-ellias/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is &#8220;Settled Science&#8221; Scientific?</title>
		<link>https://dwaynedavies.com/is-settled-science-scientific/</link>
					<comments>https://dwaynedavies.com/is-settled-science-scientific/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dwayne Davies]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 09:59:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Epistemology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Physics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quotes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[certainty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hume]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[knowledge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[logic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Metaphysics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[proof]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[quote4s]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://metaphysicsofphysics.com/?p=20906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some people, including alleged champions of reason and science think that there is no such thing as settled science. Let's bust that unscientific nonsense.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Is there any such thing as settled science? I am going to argue that there is.</p>



<p>What do I mean by &#8220;settled&#8221; science? A scientific claim that any rational person would accept as true and established beyond any reasonable doubt. We do not expect such theories to be replaced by an alternate theory.</p>



<p>You might object that this is not very scientific! We must always keep in mind that we might be wrong. We need to be ready to adjust what we know to accommodate new information that might cast what we know today into doubt. Keep in mind that we are fallible and that we might come to invalid conclusions.</p>



<p>All knowledge, including science, is contextual. We study reality and, based on what we observe, we form logical conclusions. But we can only account for that we know about.</p>



<p>For instance, take Newtonian gravity. In the context of not knowing what happens near the speed of light, it was entirely reasonable to accept Newton&#8217;s laws of gravity as settled science. We did not know what happened at extremely high velocities, so we had no reason to doubt Newtonian gravity. Newtonian gravity is valid, within the context of things not moving close to the speed of light. </p>



<p>We then expanded our context to account for things near light speed. We realized that in that context, Einstein’s relativity provides better mathematics for what happens with gravity at near light speed. Does that mean that we had no reason to be certain about Newtonian gravity? </p>



<p>No, it does not. We knew it was an accurate description of gravity at speeds much lower than the speed of light.</p>



<p>That is why NASA uses Newtonian gravity for most purposes, even though relativistic equations would be more accurate. Newtonian gravity is easier to deal with and is extremely accurate at the speeds NASA works with.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="500" height="559" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg" alt="Space shuttle launch." class="wp-image-26162" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch.jpg 500w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/space-shuttle-launch-268x300.jpg 268w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">You may have noticed rockets do not go at anything near the speed of light. So, Newton&#8217;s gravity equations will work just fine thanks.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Certainty is contextual. Suppose, in the context of our knowledge, the available evidence supports a theory. We should be certain about that theory. But what we are wrong? After all, we used to believe some strange things.</p>



<p>We used to think things burned because of phlogiston. Phlogiston was a mysterious substance that was thought to exist in all combustible bodies.</p>



<p>We used to think that dinosaurs were all sluggish, scaly critters that probably lived in swamps to support their massive weight.</p>



<p>Yes, sometimes we are wrong. Sometimes the facts do not support our theories. There are some theories that we have no business accepting as anything more than a plausible hypothesis.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="these-are-the-theories-that-do-not-make-up-the-body-of-settled-science-these-are-the-theories-we-should-not-consider-settled">These are the theories that do not make up the body of settled science. These are the theories we should not consider settled. </h3>


<p>It would be dishonest to consider a theory settled in the absence of evidence. It would also be dishonest to consider a theory settled if we did not understand it well enough to be sure it was consistent with all the available evidence.</p>



<p>Some theories are entirely reasonable within the context of the available evidence. Sometimes all the known evidence points to these theories being true. </p>



<p>Sometimes we understand the theory well enough to conclude it is entirely consistent with the facts. If the facts are consistent with that theory and only that theory, then we can be certain that the theory in question is true.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="we-should-not-entertain-serious-doubts-about-theories-that-have-substantial-evidence-behind-them">We should not entertain serious doubts about theories that have substantial evidence behind them. </h3>


<p>We can always <em>imagine</em> that we might disprove some theories. However, we should be certain about a theory if all the available evidence points to it being true.</p>



<p>Certainty does not require us to account for, by magic, for the possibility of a context of knowledge we do not currently possess. We can be certain that something is true even if there is something we do not know about now that may later show that it is not true.</p>



<p>Certainty is contextual, it is valid to be certain based on the context of available evidence. Provided that we are willing to address any evidence that arises, should the context of our knowledge change. We can be certain something is true. And yet adjust our theories when the context of our knowledge expands.</p>



<p>However, there are theories that we can consider completely and forever settled. These are theories we know with certainty and can prove with no shadow of a doubt to be true.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="we-know-these-facts-are-true-and-that-we-cannot-show-them-to-be-false">We know these facts are true and that we cannot show them to be false.</h3>


<p>It would contradict known facts of reality if they were not true. Things would have to not be what we know they are.</p>



<p>Examples of these would be that atoms exist. We know atoms exist; we have seen them. If they did not exist, almost everything we know about chemistry and atomic physics would not be true.</p>



<p>We know evolution happens. We might not know everything about how it happens, but we know it does. If I wanted disprove evolution, we would have to invalidate almost everything we know about biology and the known facts of biology would have to be other than what they are.</p>



<p>We know the Earth is round and that it orbits the Sun. To invalidate this, the direct evidence of our senses would have to be wrong! That we can see that the Earth is round would have to be fake. And how would we explain the observed behavior of Earth if it does not orbit the Sun? </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="450" height="450" src="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-26164" srcset="https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller.jpg 450w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-300x300.jpg 300w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-150x150.jpg 150w, https://dwaynedavies.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/FlatEarthSmaller-70x70.jpg 70w" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">It is much more scientific to think this might be real, right?</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>We can say without a shadow of a doubt that theories like this are absolutely and forever settled and that we will never find anything that contradicts them. No such evidence is even <a href="https://dwaynedavies.com/the-possible-and-the-impossible/" data-type="post" data-id="35">possible</a>. </p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="we-completely-settled-such-science-it-would-be-nonsensical-to-pretend-otherwise">We completely settled such science. It would be nonsensical to pretend otherwise!</h3>


<p>So yes, there is such a thing as settled science. It is foolish to pretend otherwise. And it would be intellectually dishonest and non-scientific to pretend that we have not settled this!</p>



<p>It is unscientific to question that the Earth might not be round. Or that evolution does not happen. Or that atoms do not exist. Why? Because we have seen that the Earth is round! Are we to question the evidence of our senses so that we can become a Flattard?</p>



<p>It would contradict the obvious implications of the evidence of our senses to believe atoms do not exist. Additionally, we have seen atoms! It would go against observable facts and their logical implications to question that evolution happens.</p>



<p>It would be unscientific to question that light behaves like a wave. This would go against the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of that evidence.</p>



<p>To question theories we can show are irrefutable facts based on the evidence of our senses and the logical implications of such, is unscientific.</p>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="your-belief-that-the-irrefutable-facts-of-reality-might-be-wrong-is-completely-nonsensical-and-unscientific">Your belief that the irrefutable facts of reality might be wrong is completely nonsensical and unscientific. </h3>


<p>The ability to entertain alternatives to the way reality works is not indicative of science. It is closer to the mindset of the religious person that must evade reality to maintain the possibility of his delusions. The questioning of everything, even things we can prove beyond any reasonable doubt, is little better than those that deny science outright. </p>



<p>To deny the absolute certainty of that which we can show beyond any reasonable doubt, is to either partially deny the veracity of the evidence or fail to understand that science is about the study of an objective reality, not blind guesswork.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://dwaynedavies.com/is-settled-science-scientific/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
